<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rights of the crovvn of England, as it is established by law. / Written in the time of the late King, by Edward Bagshaw Esquire, an apprentice of the common-law.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1749_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77186)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 218:E1749[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rights of the crovvn of England, as it is established by law. / Written in the time of the late King, by Edward Bagshaw Esquire, an apprentice of the common-law.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 126, [10] p. : ill. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Simon Miller at the Starre in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With preliminary and final blank leaves.</note>
                  <note>Signatures K-K3 bear publisher's advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHTS OF THE CROWN <hi>OF</hi> England, As it is eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
            <p>Written in the time of the Late King, By <hi>Edward Bagſhaw</hi> Eſquire, an Apprentice of the Common-Law.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Ad Conſervationem Jurium Coronae noſtrae, eò nos decet ſtudioſius operam adhibere, quó ad hoc aſtringimur Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo Juramenti, <bibl>Regiſt. fol. <hi>61.</hi> b.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Antiqua Maneria Coronae annexa; Regi non licebit alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare: ſed omnis Rex Coronae ſuae alienata revocare te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur, <bibl>
                  <hi>Fleta</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Simon Miller</hi> at the Starre in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST Excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt great and moſt gracious Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ring my long Impriſonment in the Kings Bench and other places, for my adherence to the Cauſe of my late Sovereign (your moſt pious Father, and Gods moſt glorious Martyr) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb facs="tcp:170328:3"/> at that time High Treaſon, and upon that ſcore I was committed Priſoner to the Kings Bench, <hi>June</hi> the <hi>29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1644.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had then leaſure to bethink my ſelf what that Treaſon was; which I could not find written in Books of <hi>Law,</hi> but on Banners of <hi>Warre;</hi> not amongſt men of the <hi>Gown,</hi> but men of the <hi>Sword:</hi> a Sword ſharpned by them at that time for the cutting down of Monarchy and
<pb facs="tcp:170328:3"/> Hierarchy, and thereby to engroſs to themſelves the rich Crop of the Kings and Biſhops Lands, which they had no poſſibility to bring about, but by making the one <hi>Tyrannicall,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon I adventured in this my reſtraint, to run the hazard of writing three Books: The firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Revenues of the Church in Tythes and Glebe. The ſecond main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Doctrine, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,
<pb facs="tcp:170328:4"/> and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as they were eſtabliſhed by Law. The laſt aſſerting the Rights of the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two former were long ſince Printed; this laſt I made ready for the Preſs, and left it in the hands of Doctor <hi>Ouldſworth</hi> for that purpoſe, <hi>Dedicating it to your Majeſties moſt Royall Father:</hi> but that ſudden and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>blow</hi> which fell upon
<pb facs="tcp:170328:4"/> him, and in him upon the whole Nation, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, confounded the <hi>Preſs,</hi> my <hi>Book,</hi> and <hi>me;</hi> a fact ſo tranſcendently hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and monſtrous, that it filled me as much with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement that it could be done; as with ſorrow that it was done.</p>
            <p>This Book brought to the birth, and thus diſpoyled of its Royall Patron, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long for the ſupport of a Sovereign Power, and
<pb facs="tcp:170328:5"/> now humbly ſupplicates your Princely Patronage, for ſtrength to bring forth; which in juſtice your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty cannot well deny, you being as well an inheritour of your Fathers Vertues, as of his Crown: nay more, a happy reſtorer of it when it was fallen, by your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to it the <hi>29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt (being your birth-day) when you were received with ſuch Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Nobility and Gentry, and with ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations
<pb facs="tcp:170328:5"/> and ſhouting for joy by all the people, that I who have lived to ſee the glory of your Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Grandfathers Reign, never ſaw the like to that triumphant Entry, which (I fear) I ſhould leſſen, ſhould I attempt to deſcribe.</p>
            <p>I am only able to liken it to the Inauguration of King <hi>Solomon;</hi> there were then ſuch blowing of Trumpets, ſuch piping with Flutes, ſuch huge ſhouts of
<pb facs="tcp:170328:6"/> all the people, with God ſave King <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the earth <hi>rent</hi> with the ſound of them; and there were ſuch rejoycings in the City of <hi>Gihon,</hi> where he was annointed King, that the City <hi>rang</hi> for joy: ſo did the City of <hi>London,</hi> when you our <hi>Solomon</hi> entred it on that day.</p>
            <p>For my own part, ſuch was my joy, that I thought it ſatisfaction and comfort enough, for the ſufferings I had undergone for above
<pb facs="tcp:170328:6"/> ſixteen yeares, in Body, Eſtate, and Profeſſion; in that God hath heard my conſtant Prayers for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of your Majeſty to your Crown; the Church of <hi>England</hi> to her Religion; the Law of <hi>England</hi> to its ancient Glory and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour; and the people of <hi>England</hi> to their <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta</hi>-Liberties.</p>
            <p>So that according to your Fathers prediction, I have ſeen you <hi>Charles le bon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Εἰκων Βασιλ <hi>Sect.</hi> 27.</note> and <hi>Charles le
<pb facs="tcp:170328:7"/> Grand.</hi> And I doubt not, but Almighty God who hath done ſuch wonderfull things for you, will ſo continue you to the end.</p>
            <p>I here conclude, humbly begging leave to pray for my Lord the King, in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of a King (your bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Father now with God) <hi>I pray God bleſs you, and eſtabliſh your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; your Soul in true Religion; and your Honour in the
<pb facs="tcp:170328:7"/> love of God and your People.</hi> And this ſhall ever be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt loyall and humbly devoted Subject <hi>Edward Bagſhaw.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 7. line 18. for <hi>&amp;c.</hi> read <hi>and.</hi> p. 8. l. 16. for <hi>Recorders</hi> r. <hi>Records.</hi> p. 10. l. 14. for <hi>quellet</hi> r. <hi>avel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</hi> p. 22. l. 4, 5. for <hi>Queen</hi> Maries <hi>Injunctions</hi> read <hi>Queens Majeſties Injunctions.</hi> p. 28. l. 4. for <hi>that King</hi> r. <hi>this King.</hi> p. 43. l. 3. for <hi>fortious Act</hi> r. <hi>tortious Act.</hi> p. 45. l. 7. read <hi>by ſome of the common people.</hi> p. 47. l. 21. read <hi>doth the word King intimate.</hi> p. 48. l. 19. dele <hi>ſo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170328:8"/>
            <head>THE RIGHTS OF THE Crown of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> as it is Eſtabliſhed by Law.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O perſwade a People arm'd with a violent Sword, to cut out to themſelves their own Government, to embrace Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy (lying under ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſloyall reproaches, which it hath received from <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi>) as the beſt Form of Government, to make them happy; may ſeem rather the work of an Angel, than of a man. But yet it will be no hard matter to perſwade <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170328:9"/> men to <hi>embrace</hi> Monarchy, under the name and notion of the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when it ſhall be made apparent to them, that in the peace thereof conſiſteth their peace, and by the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and majeſty of the Crown, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Eaſe and Juſtice,</hi> the two darling delights of the People.</p>
            <p>If men did but conſider the glory and beauty of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as it is in it ſelf, and as it ſtands in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the people, in thoſe two lovely properties of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> it would draw all hearts to love it, all hands to defend it, all pens to write for it, and all tongues to plead for it. For what is it elſe, but that <hi>Supream Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſcription.</note> 
               <hi>given by God the founder of it, to the King, and ſo acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the people; annexed by Law to the natural body of the King; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it united and incorporated, for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all his Subjects in peace and ſafety, according to the Laws of the Land?</hi> This is briefly the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of it, which I will now forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie with ſome Reaſons and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170328:9"/>
            <p>And for a more ſuccinct proving of all the parts of this deſcription, I ſhall make good theſe ſix concluſions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Soveraigne Power belonging to the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>is, according to the Law of the Land, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the King by God, not by the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That it is ſo aſſented to by the People of</hi> England; <hi>and this their aſſent openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by divers Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That this Soveraigne Power, is by Law inſeparably
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170328:10"/> and undividedly united to the naturall Body of the King, and maketh in him but one Royal Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That this Soveraigne Power is over all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of</hi> England, <hi>as well in a Collective Body, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, as over every ſingular Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That this Power is given to the King, as well for the preſervation of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as for the Governement of all his People in peace and ſafety.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170328:10"/>6. <hi>That this Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be according to the Laws of the Land, not by an Arbitrary Illegall Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the more ſincere handling of all theſe, I ſhall indeavour to avoid theſe two Rocks:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Flattery of the King, a vice which King <hi>James</hi> calls,<note place="margin">Baſi. l Doron. <hi>lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>peſt</hi> of all <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>wrack</hi> of <hi>Republicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Injury of the People, (the unruly ringleader of all Sedition and Rebellion:) and truly to ſtate the Praerogative of the King, as it relates to the liberty of the people, in joyning them together in marriage (as the Law hath joyned them) with an indiſſoluble knot.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt Concluſion; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Law of Reaſon be the<note n="*" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>&amp; Stu.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 5.</note> firſt Ground of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and from thence I might inſiſt upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170328:11"/> that Argument mentioned by thoſe two Patriarks of Philoſophy and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plato</hi> lib. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>de Leg.</hi> Ariſto. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> lib. <hi>Pol.</hi> cap. 30.</note> (the Maſter and the Scholler) That the chiefeſt perſon in every houſhold is in nature of a King; and when numbers of Families joyned themſelves in civil ſocieties, Kings were the firſt kind of Governours; and from thence inforce this Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</p>
            <p>That as the Fathers of Families have (by the conſent of all Oppoſites to Monarchy at this day) their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment immediately from God, ſo have the Fathers of their Countries. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing hath been more tortured upon the rack than the Law of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I will only hold my ſelf for the proof of this point, to the poſitive Laws of this Kingdome, from the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King of it, to this very day.</p>
            <p>I will begin with King <hi>Lucius,</hi> who after he had received the Chriſtian faith almoſt fifteen hundred years agone, by the meanes of <hi>Eleutherius</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (the moſt pious Father of the the Church then living) he writes to that Biſhop to ſend to him the <hi>Romane</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170328:11"/> Laws (then famous over the world) whereby he might the better Governe the People of <hi>England.</hi> The good Biſhop writes to him an Epiſtle back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,<note place="margin">Lamb. inter. Leg. <hi>Edw.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anno. Dom.</hi> 169 (as I find it printed amongſt the Laws of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, put forth by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lambert</hi>) and ſtiles him in that Epiſtle, <hi>Vicarius Dei in Regno ſuo;</hi> Gods Vicegerent in his own Kingdome: and adviſeth him to reject the Laws of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to chooſe a Law <hi>ex utraque pagina,</hi> from the Old and New Teſtament, and by that to Governe his People. Now the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are more agreeable to the Laws of God, than the Laws of any Commonwealth, <hi>Grecian, Roman,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though without much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty it might be proved; yet being not to the Point I have in hand, I will paſſe it by, and only prove this; That according to that ſtile of <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> The Kings of <hi>England</hi> have by the Laws thereof, and by the conſtitution of this Kingdome from that day to this, been accounted Gods immediate Lievete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and to have the Supreame So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Power from God in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170328:12"/> Kingdomes, and not from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The Laws of <hi>England</hi> from the daies of this <hi>Lucius,</hi> and the ſucceeding Kings, till the dayes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, were cut in pieces by the ſharp Sword of Civil Warre, which continued here in <hi>England</hi> for divers hundred of years, (that of the <hi>Danes</hi> alone continuing two hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,) and divided into the Laws of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> called <hi>Marchen-leg,</hi> into the Laws of the <hi>Danes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leg. Edw.</hi> c. 1.</note> called <hi>Dane-leg,</hi> and into the Laws of the Weſt-<hi>Saxons,</hi> called <hi>Weſtſaxon-leg.</hi> This good King <hi>Edward,</hi> (for ſo the Recordors of that time call him) out of the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken pieces of theſe Laws, choſe twelve of the moſt learned men of the Law within the Realme, to compile one entire compleate Body of the Law, and Cuſtomes of the Kingdome; charging them upon an Oath, that they ſhould performe it juſtly and truely, not turning to the right hand or to the left; <hi>Nihil praetermittentes, nihil addentes, nihil mutantes,</hi> as the words of that Law are: which they did according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170328:12"/> and that King Enacted it to be uſed commonly throughout the whole Kingdome, from whence it had the appellation of the Common Law; and not upon that ground given by a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Commons-houſe, in the beginning of this Parliament;<note place="margin">Hen. Martin.</note> 
               <hi>That Common Law was nothing, but Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon; and therefore he ſaw no cauſe why a Gentleman in a ſhort Cloake, might not declare what was the Law of the Realme, as well as a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the long Robe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words of my Author are theſe, <hi>Ex immenſa legum congerie, quas Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani, Romani, Angli, Daci condiderunt, optima quaeque ſelegit, ac in unam co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egit, quam vocari voluit Communem Legem.</hi> Theſe Laws and Cuſtomes are ſet down in ſeverall Chapters vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called, St. <hi>Edwards</hi> Laws, which are in ſubſtance the ſame with our <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> and which the Kings of this Realme heretofore at their Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſwore chiefly to obſerve,<note place="margin">Vet. N. bre. <hi>fol. 164.</hi> Juramentum Regis. Leg. Edw. <hi>c. 17.</hi>
               </note> in theſe words; <hi>Praeſertim Leges, conſuetudines, &amp; libertates à glorioſo Rege Edwardo, clero populoque conceſſas,</hi> as it is at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170328:13"/> large expreſſed in the Oath of the King at his Coronation in the <hi>M. Charta,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno. Dom.</hi> 1656. in the 17. Chapter of that Law, under the Title, <hi>de Officio Regis.</hi> The King of <hi>England</hi> is ſtiled, as in the dayes of <hi>Lucius, Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſummi Regis,</hi> the Lievtenant of the higheſt King. The words of the Law run thus; <hi>Rex autem quia Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſummi Regis eſt, ad hoc eſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutus, ut regnum terrenum &amp; populum Domini &amp; ſuper omnia ſanctam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam ejus regat, &amp; ab injurioſis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendat &amp; maleficos ab ea quellet &amp; destruat &amp; penitus diſperdat.</hi> Theſe Laws are much refined by King <hi>H.</hi> 1. the Conquerours Son ſurnamed <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clerke;</hi> but much more by <hi>H.</hi> 2. his grandchild, who wrote a book intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>pro Republica, Leges:</hi> of which there remaines not any fragment at this day: only the book of <hi>Glanvile</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> and a Book called <hi>Regia Majeſtas,</hi> both written in King <hi>H.</hi> 2. dayes, of the Cuſtomes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> do both of them make the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Power of the King of <hi>England</hi> to be immediately from God.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170328:13"/>
            <p>King <hi>H.</hi> 2. compiled alſo an other Book, called <hi>Statuta Regalia,</hi> which to the puniſhment of this Kingdome was unhappily loſt. For by want of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down the particular Rights of the Crowne, chiefly in the Laws of the Forreſt, moſt grievous to the Subject, and over liberall to the Crown, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe great afforeſtations made by himſelf and his two Sonnes, <hi>Rich.</hi> 1. and King <hi>John,</hi> grew thoſe long blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and rebellious Warres (for ſo do Hiſtorians call them) of the Barons, laſting about ſixty years in the dayes of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Ch. de For. <hi>cap. 1.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> for the ſetling and confirming the great Charter of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the Charter of the Forreſt, agreed unto by King <hi>John,</hi> in the 17. year of his Raign, and Enacted by Parliament in the 9. year of <hi>H.</hi> 3. while he was in his minority; and ſolemnly afterward confirmed in Parliament, when he was of full age. And yet notwithſtanding theſe Civil Warres, <hi>Bracton</hi> a learned Writer of the Law in thoſe troubleſome dayes of <hi>H.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Stat. de Marle. <hi>cap. 5.</hi>
               </note> and a Judge of the Realme, and one that profeſſeth of himſelf, that he did with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170328:14"/> exceeding labour and paines ſearch out diligently <hi>antiqua Juſtorum judicia,</hi> (for ſo he ſtileth the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> the ancient judgements of the juſt) doth ſtile <hi>H.</hi> 3. in the time of the Warres againſt him by his Barons, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtile given before to <hi>Edw.</hi> the Confeſſor, <hi>Vicarius Dei;</hi> His words are theſe, <hi>Rex autem cùm ſit Dei Vicarius in terra, ſeparare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet jus ab injuria, aequum ab iniquo, ut omnes ſibi ſubjecti honeſtè vivant &amp; nullus alium laedat; Potentia omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſibi ſubjectis debet praecellere,</hi> &amp;c. Which words are in themſelves a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Confutation of thoſe two ſeditious diſtinctions, lately ſprung up againſt the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> by ſome Divines and worſe Lawyers; That the King is the Supreame Perſon, but not the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Power. That he is, <hi>ſingulis major,</hi> but <hi>univerſis minor:</hi> whenas the words of <hi>Bracton</hi> are full, That he hath a Soveraigne Power over all his Subjects univerſally; and if ſo, then over them all, as they are united in one Body, as over every ſingular perſon. But theſe two diſloyall diſtinctions I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170328:14"/> ſhall have occaſion more particularly to refute, when I come to prove my fourth Concluſion; and then I ſhall make them as irrationall as they are il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Britton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brit.</hi> fol. 1.</note> another ancient Writer of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith thus of the King; That he is ordained of God, that the Peace be kept,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Co.</hi> 11. <hi>Rep.</hi> 72. Plow. <hi>f.</hi> 115.</note> and therefore he is called by latter Authorities, Gods Lievetenant, the Fountain of Juſtice and of common Right, the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon in the Realme, and to have the moſt excellent things that are in the Earth and in the Sea.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of this Ordination from God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>F. N. br.</hi> 21. Plow. 234. Plow. 238. Plow. 242, <hi>&amp;</hi> 243. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 4. Plow. Dame <hi>Hales</hi> Caſe. Plow. 177. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 10.</note> he is ſaid in Law to have divers divine reſemblances; as ubiquity, to be preſent in all his Courts, and in all places of his Kingdome; a kind of Omnipotency in the Attributes of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Mercy, diſtributing them to all his People, whereupon he is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Law the Fountain of Juſtice and Mercy. Nay he is reported by <hi>Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> to be the chief Head of the Law, <hi>fol.</hi> 242, 243, &amp; 502. Immortality, in that he never dies, hath no infancy, no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170328:15"/> folly, no corruption of blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The King ſaith <hi>Plowden,</hi> a learned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Author of Law, is a name of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, which ſhall alwayes endure, as Head and Governour of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Many more Authorities may be cited in this nature, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake I omit. I will only adde one Authority more, and conclude with it, becauſe it fully proves my firſt Concluſion. <hi>Bracton</hi> in his firſt Book, handling on purpoſe the Soveraigne Power of the King, hath theſe words, <hi>Ipſe autem Rex non debet eſſe ſub ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ſub Deo,</hi> A King (ſaith he) ought not to be under man, but God; and he gives a notable reaſon for it: For if the King ſhould be dependant upon men, thoſe men muſt have an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall Power with the King, or a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Power; if an equall, then the King ſhould have no Power, for (ſaith he) <hi>Par in parem poteſtatem non habet,</hi> one equall hath not juriſdiction over his Companion; if a Superiour Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, then ſhould he be no King, but a Subject, and ſo without Soveraignty. And therefore as a man expert in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170328:15"/> Laws and Cuſtomes of the Realme, he ſets down the Conſtitution of the Crowne of <hi>England</hi> that all are ſubject to him, but he to none but only to God; <hi>Omnis ſub eo, &amp; ipſe ſub nullo, niſi tantum ſub Deo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is here objected by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:<note place="margin">Ob.</note> It may be true that you ſay, that this is the Law of <hi>England</hi> concerning the Soveraigne Power of Kings; but how doth it appear that this Law was not impoſed, or enforced upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? If you can prove it, ſay they (and ſo I have heard ſome ſpeak) that the people of <hi>England</hi> have aſſented to this Law, God forbid that any ſhould be ſo wicked as to oppoſe it, and ſo execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as to reſiſt it, contrary to their own conſent, but to truſt God with the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and event of things in whoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it is alone <hi>to looſe the bond of Kings, and gird their loynes with a girdle</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>and who will puniſh their faults the more ſeverely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ser. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jo. Burgeſs</hi> 19. <hi>Junii</hi> at Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Court. An. D. 1604.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe none can do it but he:</hi> as a learned and pious Preacher ſpake before King <hi>James</hi> in the behalf of all the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Miniſters then in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170328:16"/> the very next year after the conference at <hi>Hampton</hi>-Court.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To which Objection I anſwer, by maintaining my ſecond Concluſion, which is this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> That this Law concerning the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty of Kings, is thus aſſented to by the People of <hi>England,</hi> and this their aſſent openly expreſſed and declared by divers Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>For the proof whereof I ſhall make good theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the People of <hi>England</hi> have aſſented to this Law by a tacite and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed aſſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By an open and manifeſt aſſent in ſundry Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>As concerning the firſt, it is to be known that the People of this Realme are Governed by three kinds of Law.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Common Law.</item>
               <item>2. Cuſtomes.</item>
               <item>3. Statute Law, or Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Common Law, which ſtandeth upon divers ancient Maximes, and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170328:16"/> of Law admitted and conſented to by the people.</p>
            <p>Cuſtomes, which are either gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally allowed throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as Gavelkind, Borough-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Copy-hold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or by preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in certain Counties, and Towns, which are likewiſe incorporated into the Body of the Common Law upon this Maxim, <hi>Conſuetudo ex rationabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li cauſa facit Jus.</hi> Now theſe two Laws do much exceed that which we call <hi>Statute Law,</hi> as being more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and fixed, leſſe mutable, and more incorrupt; as might aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be proved, were it incident to the point in Queſtion. It is by this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, before any Statute was made, that the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is not dependent on any other than God alone (this kind of Independan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the Law doth alow, but not ſome other:) I ſay, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, which hath this Priviledge above all humane Laws, (the Laws of the <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) That no man could ever ſtand up, and ſay, that he was the firſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170328:17"/> Lawgiver to this Nation, (like <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> and <hi>Solon</hi> amongſt the <hi>Greeks, Papirius</hi> and <hi>Sempronius</hi> amongſt the <hi>Romanes:</hi>) For neither did the King make his own Prerogative, nor the Judges the Rules and Grounds of Law; nor did the people preſcribe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves their own Rights and Liberties; but what Liberties and Cuſtomes had been by long tract of time aſſented unto, approved and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed by Prince and People, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing to the Laws of God, that ever was, and is ſtill, the Common Law: Amongſt which Liberties and Cuſtomes, this of the Sovereignty of Kings from God over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is by <hi>Glanvile, Bracton,</hi> and the Mirrour of Juſtices, (a Book treating of the Cuſtomes of <hi>England</hi> before the Conqueſt) made to be one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will now come to the ſecond thing, and prove this Sovereign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Crown immediately from God, to be expreſly and openly aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to by the people in ſundry Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170328:17"/>
            <p>I will firſt begin with the Act of Parliament of 16. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">16. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. c. 5.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it took its riſe from the humble deſires of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> as appears by the Preamble of that Statute, wherein they all make an acknowledgment in theſe very words, <hi>That the Crown of</hi> England <hi>hath been ſo free at all times, that it hath been in no earthly ſubjection, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſubject to God in all things touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Regality of the ſaid Crown, and to no other.</hi> And ſo was it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly enacted by the Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 31.</note> All the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (at whoſe humble ſuite that Law was made) do there declare it for a Maxim and Ground of Law, <hi>That the Realm of</hi> England <hi>recognizeth no Superiour under God but only the King.</hi> Which authority alſo the whole Clergy of <hi>England</hi> recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in their Synods and Convocations, as appears by that Statute.</p>
            <p>But in the Parliament of 28. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">28. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 10.</note> there is a more full expreſſion, where it is declared by the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>That the Kings Majeſty is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170328:18"/> the only Supream Head of the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and that this Right, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Preheminence is due unto him by the Law of God.</hi> And in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did the Crown of <hi>England</hi> ſit upon the Head of Kings <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and King <hi>Edw.</hi> his Sonne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. P. <hi>&amp;</hi> M. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> till Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> loving the Popes Crown better than her own, repealed ſome of this power, and placed it in the Pope, which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the firſt year of her Reign took away,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored it in the ſame plight as it was in the daies of her Father King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. only changing but a word, <hi>Supream Governour</hi> for <hi>Supream Head;</hi> the ſame in ſubſtance, though a fitter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in regard of the Honour ſhe bare to her Saviour, to whom ſhe thought the tytle of Supream Head, in reſpect of the Church, more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to belong; Whereupon ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the two Oathes that were made in Parliament <hi>An.</hi> 26,<note place="margin">26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 1.</note> and 28. of the Reign of her Father, to the Oath that now is taken throughout the Kingdom, and which every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to take,<note place="margin">28. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 10.</note> by the Statute of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170328:18"/> 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1.</note> ere he can ſit in the Houſe of Commons, or have a vote there. As namely, <hi>That our Sovereign Lord King</hi> Charles, <hi>is the only Supream Governour of this his Realm, and of all other his Highneſs Dominions and Countries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>as well in all Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical things or cauſes as Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> &amp;c. Which general words touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings Supreamacy, are now to be expounded by thoſe Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. which I mentioned before, and do contain within them theſe three Properties;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Kings Supream Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is immediately from God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Realm of <hi>England</hi> hath no Superiour under God (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be any or many perſons, for the word Superiour includeth both) but only the King.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this Honour and Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of the King, is due unto him by the Law of God.</p>
            <p>And that this is no expoſition of mine, but the true genuine expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law, It is provided by the Statute of 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 1.</note> that the Oath of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170328:19"/> Supreamacy made in the firſt year of Queen <hi>Eliz. ſhall be taken and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in ſuch form as is ſet forth in An Admonition annexed to the Queen</hi> Maries <hi>Injunctions publiſhed in the firſt year of her Majeſties Reign:</hi> That is to ſay, to confeſſe and acknowledge in her Majeſty, her Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, none other Authority than was challenged and lately uſed by the Noble King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. And that Authority, together with all Dignities, Regalities, and Preheminences belonging to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> are by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Recognition of 1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 3.</note> declared to be as rightfully and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Veſted in her, as they were in the late King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. as by that Statute may at large appear: Some of which Regalities were, that the Crown is dependent on God alone, and ſubject to no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour under him; And this to be due to him by the Law of God.</p>
            <p>I might add more Statutes to prove this point: I will only conclude with one Statute more, enacted within my
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170328:19"/> own remembrance, and the beſt in that kind that ever was made in my daies, and the moſt emphatically pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It is the Statute of Recognition made in the firſt year of King <hi>James</hi> by the whole Parliament,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Jac.</hi> cap. 1.</note> which I will write more largely, becauſe there are many memorable things in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They acknowledge the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God upon this Kingdom, in the Unions of the Houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> eſpecially of the two Kingdomes <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> under King <hi>James,</hi> and thereby free from bloody civil warres.</p>
            <p>Next, They teſtifie their unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able joy for his Majeſties moſt happy Inauguration and Coronation.</p>
            <p>Then they agnize upon the knees of their hearts (it is their own expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) their moſt conſtant faith, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and loyalty to his Majeſty, and his Royal Progeny (of which our now Sovereign Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> was then an Infant about three years old.)</p>
            <p>Afterwards, in moſt lowly and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, they beſeech his moſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170328:20"/> excellent Majeſty, That (as a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to all Poſterity amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of his High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ever to endure, of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, obedience, and hearty and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection,) it might be publickly declared and enacted in the High Court of Parliament; That they (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bounden thereunto by the Laws of God and man) did with unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able joy, recognize and acknowledge, that immediately upon the deceaſe of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Imperial Crown of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and the Rights belonging to the ſame, (of which this point of the Sovereignty of the Crown from God was a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal one,) did by inherent Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and lawfull ſucceſſion, diſcend and come to his moſt excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as next and ſole Heir of the Blood-Royal of this Realm. And to this Recognition <hi>we do</hi> (ſay they) <hi>muſt humbly and faithfully ſubmit and obleige our ſelves and Poſterities for ever, untill the laſt drop of our blood be ſpent. And we do beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to accept the ſame, as the firſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170328:20"/> fruits in this High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of our Loyalty and faith to your Majeſty, and to your Royall Progeny and Poſterity for ever.</hi> And in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Act, they have theſe words; <hi>Which if your Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed (as an argument of your gracious acceptation) to adorne with your Majeſties Royall aſſent (without which it can neither be compleat nor perfect; nor remain to all Poſterity, according to our moſt humble deſires, as a memoriall of your Princely and tender affection towards us) we ſhall adde this alſo to the rest of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties unſpeakable and uneſtimable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Statute theſe things are obſervable:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this Act of Parliament doth not give any manner of Title to the King or his Poſterity, to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> but this Right and Title to the Crown, is expreſly ſaid to be by the Laws of God and man, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent birthright, and lawfull ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: And therefore they humbly deſire, this their Recognition may be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170328:21"/> accepted of him, as a teſtimony of their conſtant faith and Loyalty to him and his Poſterity for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They do not ſubject the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to any forefeiture to the people, or to any conditionall Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in Governement, by way of preſervation of Religion, Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but leave it pure and free according to the Laws I cited before, without any condition, which the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Law doth not admit of; as I ſhall more fully ſhew in the proof of my fourth Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they put no conditions upon the Crown, ſo they put no conditions upon their own Obedience and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but freely and abſolutely oblige themſelves and their poſterities for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to this their Recognition to King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> his Sonne, and to their Poſterity, to the ſpending of the laſt drop of their blouds.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though the two Houſes of Lords and Commons, with one una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent <hi>(nullo contradicente)</hi> agreed upon this Act of Parliament,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170328:21"/> and though it was for the publick peace and tranquillity of King and People, yet they acknowledged that it was not compleate or perfect, or could remain as a Law to Poſterity, unleſs the King did give his Royall aſſent to it. The new light and new Law of making Laws in Parliament, binding to the people, without the Royall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, were not known to this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though as wiſe and as learned men were of it, as ever were either before or ſince.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That though it was an Act of publick concernement, yet they do not deſire the King ſhould paſs it out of duty, which he could neither will nor chooſe (as the late Language hath been) but that he would paſs it as an Act of his grace and ten der affection to them; And what is of grace is not of duty and right.</p>
            <p>They laſtly deſire, it may remaine amongſt the Records of Parliament, as a memoriall to all poſterity for ever to endure, of the Loyalty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of them and their Poſterity, to that King and his Progeny for ever;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170328:22"/> And how this Recognition, according to this Obligation, hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them and their Children; to that King and his Poſterity, I had much rather weep, than ſpeak in it: The Lord of Heaven adde it not to that meaſure of iniquity in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preſſed down and running over with blood.</p>
            <p>And as this is the Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England,</hi> concerning this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Power in the Crown; So it is the Divinity of the Kingdome, as may appeare by the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the 37. Article of Religion, in theſe words; <hi>The Queens Majesty hath the chief Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in this Realme of</hi> England, <hi>and other her Dominions, unto whom the chief Governement of all Eſtates of this Realme, whether they be Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall or Civill, in all Cauſes doth appertain.</hi> By which the King of <hi>England</hi> is made to have the chief Power, againſt that ſeditious and new-found diſtinction infuſed into the head of the People, by ſome as ignorant of Religion as of Law: That the King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170328:22"/> of <hi>England</hi> is the Supreame Perſon or Governour, but not the Supreame Power.</p>
            <p>I will ſhut up all I have more to ſay upon this Point,<note place="margin">King <hi>James</hi> Remonſtrance againſt Card. <hi>Peron.</hi>
               </note> with the only Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of King <hi>James</hi> in his moſt learned Defence for the Right of Kings, againſt Cardinall <hi>Peron;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he unanſwerably handles this Point againſt <hi>Bellarmine, Mariana,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jeſuites; and againſt ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants (whetting their Swords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings at the forge of thoſe <hi>Philiſtims:</hi>) Of which exquiſite Piece I may ſay with <hi>Solomon</hi> upon another Subject, <hi>What can the man do,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>that cometh after the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My third Concluſion is this; <hi>That <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> this Kingly Power, is by Law inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and individedly united to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body of the King, and make in him but one entire Royall Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Perſon of the King is by Law made up of two bodies, A naturall body, ſubject to Infancy, infirmity, ſickneſs and death, And a politick body, perfect, powerfull, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: Theſe two bodies are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170328:23"/> and individedly united together, and conſolidate in each other.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plow. Duchy</hi> of <hi>Lanchaſters</hi> Caſe. 2 13.</note> 
               <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus corporatum</hi> (ſaith the Law) <hi>in Corpore naturali, &amp; Corpus naturale in Corpore corporato;</hi> So that you may diſtinguiſh them, but not divide them. This union is like that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Soul and the Body; The Soul it animates, it quickens, it beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the body; ſo this politick body dignifies, or (rather to ſpeak in a Law-phraſe) it magnifies the naturall body of the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plow.</hi> 213.</note> by greatning it with a threefold greatneſs.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of Perfection.</item>
               <item>2. Of Power.</item>
               <item>3. Of Majeſty.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of Perfection, By freeing the perſon of the King from infancy, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, infirmity, impotency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of Power, By giving him a command over all his Subjects, and by Ruling and Governing them, and and not they him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of Majeſty, By making him the Fountaine of all Honour, of all Juſtice, and of all Mercy within the Realme.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170328:23"/>
            <p>Three the moſt orient and flagrant flowers of the Crown, and which no Subject can challenge; for all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects put together, are but as the Trunk of the body in man to the Head, which without the Head, can no more Rule and Governe the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body in Order and Honour, than the leaſt finger or toe; And therefore if they ſhould all preſume to joyne without the King, to conferre Honour, Juſtice, or Mercy upon any of their fellow-Subjects, that Honour is accounted in Law but a Tumour, the Juſtice they ſhould diſtribute is but Tyranny, and the Mercy they beſtow is but a ſpecious Injury. A notable Caſe in proof of this, is that of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. who when he was Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> was with many Lords and Commons that took his part againſt <hi>Rich.</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> (a King in fact, but a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Title, ſaith a learned Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) attainted of High-treaſon in the dayes of that King. At the battle of <hi>Redmore-downe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bal.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. fol. 1.</note> near <hi>Boſworth</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> on the 22. day of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1485. the Earle got the Victory, ſlew
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170328:24"/> 
               <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. in the field, and on the ſame day took the Crown upon him, and aſſumed the ſtile of a King; and in <hi>September</hi> following (and before his Coronation) ſummoned a Parliament to begin the 7. day of <hi>November</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>On the firſt day of this Parliament, the Judges were all met together in the Exchecker Chamber, to reſolve a very rare and perplexed Caſe, and ſuch as had not happened ſince the Conqueſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. fol. 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>viz. What ſhould be done about the reverſall of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainders of the King, and of divers Lords, and many Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes that were to ſit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that day.</hi> This Queſtion (the Kingdome at that time being in ſuch exigence) had been of no difficulty, if thoſe learned Judges had been <hi>Conu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> of any ſuch Law, That an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the two Houſes without the Kings actuall aſſent, had been as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall as an Act of Parliament. But neither they nor their Fathers ever heard or read of ſuch Law, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they fell upon this Reſolution;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170328:24"/> That as concerning the Lords and Commons that were attainted, they adviſed not to ſit in Parliament, till an Act of Parliament was paſſed by the other Lords and Commons not attainted, and aſſented to by the King for the reverſall of thoſe Attainders, and after the reverſall, then all of them to ſit in the Houſes; For that it was not convenient, that any ſhould ſit as Judges in thoſe Houſes that were attainted. And as concerning the King they thus Reſolved (ſaith my Authour) <hi>That the Crown takes away all defects and ſtops in bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bac.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>H.</hi> 7. p. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and that from the time the King did aſſume the Crown, the Fountain was cleared, and all attainders and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bloud diſcharged.</hi> But yet for honours ſake it was Ordered by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; That all Records wherein there was any memory or mention of the Kings Attainder, ſhould be defaced, cancelled, and taken off the File. But King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. thought it not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent any Act of reverſall ſhould in any wiſe paſs concerning him, as knowing that the Title to the Crown of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170328:25"/> had its dependance on God and the Law, and not on the people; And therefore the grace of pardoning ſuch Offenders as took up armes againſt him, being an Act of Mercy belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Crown, he would not paſs by Parliament, that thereby he might the better impropriate the thanks to himſelf: And publiſhed his Royall Proclamation to that purpoſe in that Parliament; likewiſe he did of himſelf and of his own grace conferre the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Lord <hi>Brook</hi> to Sr. <hi>Rob. Willoughby,</hi> of <hi>Lord Dawbeny,</hi> to Sr. <hi>Giles Dawbeny,</hi> and of the Earl of <hi>Bath,</hi> to the Lord <hi>Chandos,</hi> without the aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Thus have I by this one ſingle Caſe, without need of adding any more, fully proved, that by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Crown to the naturall body of the King, his Royall Perſon partakes of many, high pre-eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Perfection, Power and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in the Acts of Juſtice, Mercy, and Honour (without any dependance or contribution from his people,) by calling of Parliaments, by pardoning
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170328:25"/> Offenders, and advancements in Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, all of them Acts of Majeſty and Soveraigne Power.</p>
            <p>This Conjunction of the Office of the King with his naturall body, doth draw to the Perſon of the King, the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Ligeance of all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.<note place="margin">7. <hi>Rep. Calvins</hi> Caſe.</note> Now Ligeance is nothing elſe in Law but the true and faithfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a Liege-man, and Subject to his Liege-Lord and Soveraigne. Not that Ligeance is only tied to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, without relation to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Perſon of the King, which was the traiterous and ſeditious diſtinction of <hi>Hugh Spencer</hi> the yonger; for which and other his Treaſons he was condemned by two ſeverall Acts of Parliament;<note place="margin">Vide Stat. in Vet. M. Ch. <hi>1556.</hi>
               </note> the one called <hi>Exilium Hugonis de Spencer,</hi> the other 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 1. For by this damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (for ſo the Law cals it in <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe) if the King ſhould not be thought by his Subjects to Governe according to his Kingly Office,<note place="margin">1. <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 1.</note> the Subject is no longer tyed to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but may riſe up in arms againſt him, which cuts in ſunder all the bonds
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170328:26"/> of Governement, as well in Families as in the Commonwealth. And ſo Children may riſe up againſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Servants againſt their Maſters, Wives againſt their Husbands, and plead for themſelves the ill governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Superiors; and ſo parties ſhall become Judges, and Subjects Soveraignes, and the world by this meanes turned into a worſe eſtate than the firſt <hi>Chaos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Law of <hi>England,</hi> which is a Law of order and decency, and not of confuſion and deformity, is quite otherwiſe: for the Ligeance of the Subject is tyed principally and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the naturall body of the King, ſuſteyning and ſupporting the Royall Majeſty, and in which it doth inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably inhere, as in its proper Subject. For Ligeance being a corporeall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is to be done to a viſible, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall, and locall Perſon; not to a thing inviſible, incorporeall, and not circumſcribed to any place (as is the Royall Dignity.) This appears plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the old Oath of Allegeance, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by all the Kings Subjects, above
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170328:26"/> the age of twelve years, in the dayes of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and long before, and is at this day given in Court-Leets, which being by <hi>Britton</hi> ſet down in <hi>Law-French,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brit.</hi> fol. 74.</note> I will truely ſet down in Engliſh, <hi>You A. B. ſhall ſwear that you ſhall be faithfull and Loyall to our Lord King</hi> Edward, (at this day King <hi>Charles) and his Heirs, and faith and Loyalty you ſhall to him hear of life and member, and of earthly Honour, and you ſhall not know of any hurt or dammage to be done to him, which you ſhall not reſiſt to your Power; So help you God.</hi> By which Oath it appears plainly, that Ligeance is a corporeall ſervice, whereby the Body, Life, and Honour of the Liege Subject, is engaged to his Soveraigne, named by his proper name King <hi>Charles,</hi> a name given to his naturall body, capable of Baptiſme onely (and to his Heirs) words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to his naturall body, as the word (Succeſſor) to his body politick (and for the preſervation of his Perſon from all hurt and dammage) things inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent only to his naturall body, for his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170328:27"/> politick capacity, <hi>viz.</hi> his Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is incapable of beating, wounding, killing, or any other hurt, being a thing inviſible, incorporeall, impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hence it is that the Ligeance of an Engliſh Subject is called naturall Ligeance, and the King is called his naturall Liege Lord, inſomuch as to compaſſe the death of the King, or to levy Warre againſt him, which are acts of violence againſt his naturall Perſon, are in all Inditements of High-Treaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cal.</hi> Caſe. 7. <hi>Rep.</hi>
               </note> ſaid to be done, <hi>contra li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantiae ſuae debitum,</hi> againſt the duty and bond of Allegiance. This old Oath of Allegiance, is by the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of <hi>Leets</hi> to be tendred to all men of the age of twelve years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, upon a Fine to be laid on his head,<note place="margin">43. <hi>E.</hi> 3. fol. 27.</note> that ſhall refuſe it; and Pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to be found for him, that he be of the good behaviour; Which Law was ſo ſtrictly obſerved in the dayes of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">1. <hi>E.</hi> 3. fol. 26.</note> that a Maſter for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning a man in his ſervice, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſworne to the King, was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented for it in the <hi>Leet,</hi> and Amerced. By this excellent Law in Court-<hi>Leets,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170328:27"/> this Realme was kept in ſuch tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and peace by King <hi>Alfred,</hi> (for ſo ancient are theſe Courts) that this King cauſed chains of Gold to be hang'd up in the high wayes, and none durſt take them away. The words of my Authour are theſe,<note place="margin">Guliel. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Reg. Ang</note> 
               <hi>Armillas aureas juberet ſuſpendi quae viantium aviditatem irritarent, dum non eſſent qui eas abriperent.</hi> Which is the more to be credited, in that it doth appear, that ſtealing and theeving were ſo rare in this Kingdome in thoſe times, That the puniſhment of theft was not made capitall till above 200 years after, to wit, in the third year of the Raigne of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Weſt.</hi> 1. c. 15.</note> Which Court Leets had they been to this day duely kept by men learned in the Laws of the Realme, as they ought to have been, (for ſo are the words of <hi>Fleta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fleta.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 6. <hi>Co.</hi> 9. <hi>rep.</hi> 48. <hi>b.</hi> 6. <hi>rep. Bulleus</hi> Caſe. <hi>fol.</hi> 77.</note> 
               <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videat ſibi dominus de ſeneſcallo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deli,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>qui in legibus &amp; ſub con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinibus provinciae, &amp; jura domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſui in omnibus tueri affectet, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Ballivos Domini in ſuis erroribus &amp; ambiguis ſciat inſtruere,</hi> &amp;c.) And not turned over to Sollicitors, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170328:28"/> Serving-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as at this day (by which meanes ſcarce a ſhadow of the ancient Juriſdiction of this Court doth remaine) this Kingdome had not ſo often and inwardly bled, by many bloudy civil Wars, to the endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Commonwealth: Like as it is to the naturall body of man, when the bloud fals into the body <hi>extra vaſa,</hi> and keeps not in the proper veynes, as Phyſicians obſerve.</p>
            <p>This faith and Ligeance to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon of the King, ſo adorned with Honour and Majeſty by the Common-Law, doth leave as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall an impreſſion of duty and Loyalty in a true born Subject to his Prince, as it doth in the heart of a Child to his Father, or of a Servant to his Maſter. For the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> &amp;c. doth belong unto Kings, and was ever ſo expounded, or elſe it is no where to be found in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. Now the ſubjection of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, is to Parents and Maſters, whether good or bad; and ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> declares the Law,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170328:28"/> 
               <hi>not only</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>for this is thank-worthy, if a man for conſcience ſake towards God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>endure grief, ſuffering wrongfully.</hi> And the like ſubjection is to Kings, whether good or bad, in the judgement of the beſt Expoſitors that ever wrote upon the 13. Chapter to the <hi>Romans.</hi> This made <hi>Hubert De Sanctâ Clârâ,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Arrow ſhot againſt King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. into his own boſome, to ſave the life of his Liege Lord: and this made <hi>Tho. Howard</hi> Earl of <hi>Surrey,</hi> ſon to <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> to fight ſtoutly for King <hi>Rich.</hi> the 3. (as hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid a Tyrant as ever trode on Engliſh mould) againſt King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked the reaſon by the King, he anſwered, (<hi>That</hi> Rich. 3. <hi>was then his Crowned King, and did he ſee the Crown ſet upon the ſtump of a Thorne,</hi> (a fit reſemblance for the King he fought for) <hi>he would fight for that ſtump, and ſo he would fight for King</hi> Hen. 7. <hi>now he was his King,</hi> which he valiantly performed to his Sonne King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, at
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170328:29"/> the battle of <hi>Flodden-field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although amongſt the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of new Sects that are ſprung up at this day, the traiterous opinion of the ſaid <hi>Hugh Spencer</hi> be revived (if Treaſon may be called a Sect,) <hi>That the Allegiance of the Subject, is onely tyed to the Office of the King,</hi> not to his Perſon; yet there was none that ever I could hear or read of, pleaded this Plea at their arreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Treaſon. But the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and common excuſe hath been, of the perſons Indicted, that they never intended hurt to the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but only to remove evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors from him, or the like, which were the pleas of the two Earles of <hi>E.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> in the latter daies of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and yet adjudged to be High Treaſon.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hill.</hi> 43. <hi>Eliz. Co.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſti.</hi> p. 12.</note> But the reaſon is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edw. Cooke,</hi> who citeth the caſe in the 3d part of his Inſtitutes. But by a private report which I have ſeen, was thus delivered by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Popham</hi> Chief Juſtice, That the Law conſtrueth Treaſons by Acts, and by thoſe Acts judgeth of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170328:29"/> and the levying of Warre by them without the Kings aſſent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Glan.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 2. <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 3. fol. 1. <hi>Co</hi> 3. <hi>Inſti.</hi> p. 9.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſortious Act at the firſt, (for that no Subject can levy Warre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Realm without authority from the King;) That the levying a War to remove a Counſellor of State, is to levy Warre againſt the King, and ſo High Treaſon. For what did let but that the ſame violence which prevailed to remove the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, might have prevailed, if not only to have removed, but to have impriſoned, depoſed, and deſtroyed the Queen, being all of them Acts of High Treaſon.</p>
            <p>I will conclude all with a ſtory of old Father <hi>Latimer,</hi> told by him touching the Lord <hi>Darcy,</hi> the Lord <hi>Huſſey,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Conſtable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lat.</hi> Sermon at <hi>Stanford.</hi> fol 56. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1635.</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the Rebellion in the North, <hi>temp. H.</hi> 8. I will barely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it in the words of that godly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and renowned Martyr, and leave the application of it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will go further with you, I have travelled in the Tower my ſelf by the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170328:30"/> Kings Commandement, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and their was S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Robert Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, <hi>the Lord</hi> Huſſey, <hi>and the Lord</hi> Darcy; <hi>and the Lord</hi> Darcy <hi>was tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me of the faithfull ſervice he had done the Kings Majesty, that dead is. If I had ſeen my Sovereign Lord in the field,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſeeing his Grace coming againſt us, I would have lighted from my horſe, and taken my ſword by the point, and yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it into his Graces hands. Mary (quoth I) in the mean time, you playd not the part of a faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, in holding with the people in a commotion and diſturbance. It hath been the craft of all Traitours to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nothing againſt the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; they never pretend the matter to the King, but to others. But Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ought not to reſiſt any Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, nor ought to do any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Kings Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>4</label> My fourth Concluſion is this, <hi>That this Sovereign Power is over all the Subjects of</hi> England, <hi>as well in a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective Body as Repreſentative, as it is over every particular Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170328:30"/>
            <p>I have before ſhewed the Nature and Conſtitution of a King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> I ſhall now ſhew the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of his Power. And becauſe in this laſt and worſt age of the world, there is ſome oppoſition againſt this by the common people, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in change, by parting with truth for errour, and receiving errour for truth, from a New-Light, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the old Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: I will therefore in the firſt place Explain this Concluſion. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I will ſhew what the Law of the Land, and the Conſtitution of the Kingdom is in it. Thirdly, I will ſhew the Reaſons of the Law in the ſame. Fourthly, I will Anſwer all Objections againſt it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, It is not queſtioned by any, but that the King hath a Sovereign Power over every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Subject, and therefore I will paſſe over that. But queſtion is made, whether the King hath a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Power over all the people in a collective Body, congregated together in one place from each cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170328:31"/> of the Land, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhebah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 20.1.</note> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were in <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peh;</hi> which I ſay he hath; and that they all put together, are but this Politick Body, of which he is Head, and therefore hath the Sovereign Power over it, as the Head hath over the Natural Body, and not that a Power over the Head: for then ſhould the Head be the only Subject in the Kingdom, and the People So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns. The like I ſay for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Body of the People, which is nothing elſe in Law, but a calling by the Kings Writ, of all the Nobility and People of the Land re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in Parliament, by certain Heads of the People, choſen by them upon their own free Elections; (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is no Repreſentative Body, as appears by the Statute of 1 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 1.</note> and is there ſo explained.) Over this Repreſentative Body, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into two Houſes of Lords and Commons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Co.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſti.</hi> fol. 3. <hi>D. &amp; Stud.</hi> fol. 43.6.</note> the King hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Sovereign Power, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Law <hi>Caput Parliamenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Concluſion thus Explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170328:31"/> I ſhall in the next place prove by the Law and conſtitution of this Kingdom, That the King hath a Sovereign Power over the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the People, as well collective, as repreſentative.</p>
            <p>Two Greek words for the Name King, do aptly expreſſe the Nature of it in our Law; Βασιλευς,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> rep. in praef.</note> ſo was our King <hi>Edgar</hi> called <hi>Anglorum Baſileus, quaſi</hi> Βασις τοῦ λαῦ, the foundation or ſupport of the people. And <hi>Homer</hi> calls the King, ποιμην λαων, the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the people. He is not Head of a particular man, but of a whole people; He is not Shepheard of a ſingle ſheep, but of a whole Flock. And therefore he is called in our Law, not the Head of one man, but of the whole Commonwealth.<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And ſo much doth the King intimate, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Dutch <hi>Koennen,</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power, becauſe his Power extends over all his People. <hi>Bracton</hi> declares it more fully and exactly, by hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it on purpoſe in the 8th Chapter of his firſt Book, where having ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reaſon of the Kings Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170328:32"/> over his Subjects, he then poſitively declares the Conſtitution of the Kingdom in theſe words; <hi>Sunt ſub Rege</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>liberi homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> &amp;c. reckoning up there the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of all the Subjects, both Lords and Commons; and then addeth theſe words; <hi>Et omnis ſub eo, &amp; ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſub nullo, tantum ſub Deo.</hi> There are (ſaith he) under the King Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of all ſorts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bract.</hi> l. 1. c. 8.</note> both Lords and Commons, and all under him, and he under none, but only under God. <hi>Omnis &amp; Nullus,</hi> are in Schools cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>ſigna univerſalitatis,</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the whole <hi>Species</hi> of men collectively, as well as every ſingular <hi>Individuum:</hi> and ſo is it there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſo underſtood. For having reckoned up before the heads of the mixt people, he concludes, <hi>Omnis ſub eo, ipſe ſub nullo;</hi> which is to ſay, That all of theſe are under the King, and he not under them: And then preſently raiſeth an Objection, which is made at this day. If the King be over all his people, and he in no caſe under them, in caſe then that the King
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170328:32"/> deny to do this people juſtice, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently makes this anſwer, <hi>Locus erit ſupplicatoni quod facta ſua cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigat &amp; emendet; quod ſi non fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit, ſatis ſufficit ei ad paenam, quod dominum expectet ultorem:</hi> That is, you muſt Petition the King to amend his faults, which if he ſhall not do, it is a ſufficient puniſhment to him, that God will be revenged on him. The like he ſpeaketh in another place: <hi>Rex omnes potentia praecellit,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bract.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 9.</note> The King exceeds all people in Power; But yet (ſaith he) his heart is in the hand of God, leaſt that power ſhould prove Tyrannicall. So by the Oath of Supremacy, the King is ſaid to be the only Supreame Governour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Dominions, in all Cauſes,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without exception, which particle <hi>Onely,</hi> excludes all co-ordinate pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with him by his Subjects, much more a Superiour Power. And <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſio firmat regulam in non exceptis,</hi> as they ſay in Schooles, The 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Religion is more fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed for Law, by the Statute in the 13. year of <hi>Eliz.</hi> which ſaith; <hi>The
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170328:33"/> King hath the chiefeſt Power in this Realme of</hi> England,<note place="margin">Art. 37.13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>unto whom the chief Governement of all Eſtates of this Realme doth appertain,</hi> &amp;c. which is as much to ſay, as that he hath the chief Government of all the people of the Realme, whether in a collective or repreſentative body, compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under the Eſtates of Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Gentry, and Commons. This made Sr. <hi>John Markham,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England</hi> tell King.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4. that he could not Arreſt any man for ſuſpicion of Treaſon or Felony, as any of his Subjects might, becauſe that if he did any of his Subjects wrong, they could have no Action againſt him, in that all originall writts are in the Kings name and he cannot ſue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But a fuller proof for the Law, and conſtitution of the Kingdome in this point, is the Statute of 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. cap. 2.<note place="margin">24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 12</note> where the Realme of <hi>England</hi> is acknowledged to be an <hi>Empire, and ſo hath been accepted in the world, governed by one Supreame Head and King, having the dignity and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eſtate of the Imperiall Crowne of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170328:33"/> the ſame, unto whom a body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, compact of all ſorts of people, divided in termes by names of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually and temporalty, been bounden over to bear next to God a naturall and humble obedience;</hi> where it is ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. that <hi>England</hi> is an Empire, and ſo was King <hi>Edgar</hi> ſtiled, <hi>Totius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae imperator:</hi> And Empire and Emperors hold their Tenure next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God; <hi>Colimus imperatorem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam à Deo ſecundum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> rep in Praefat. ex Chart. <hi>Edgard. Tertul.</hi> ad Scap.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the King of <hi>England</hi> is head, not of ſingle people, but of a body Politick, Collective of all ſorts of people; Repreſentative, of degrees of people, the terms of ſpiritualty and temporalty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this Collective and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative body, do owe to the King as a debt, a duty, not a courteſie, all naturall and humble obedience without putting conditions on it.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that the two Houſes of Parliament, being the Repreſentative body of the Kingdome, do in their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170328:34"/> Bills of Parliament tendred to the King,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 4. 1. <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 1. 2. <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 2.</note> ſtile themſelves ſometimes, your moſt humble, faithfull, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Subjects; ſometimes, your moſt humble and loyall Subjects; and ſometimes, your moſt loyall, faithfull, and true-hearted Subjects. And it is impoſſible, moſt humble, faithfull, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, loyall, and true-hearted Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſhould have a coercive, coactive, and punitive power, over their Liege-Lord. With this Law the prayers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do agree, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by three ſeverall Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and uſed in the times of four Princes, King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles;</hi> by which the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of all the people do acknowledg, that God is the King of Kings, and the only Ruler of Princes; that King <hi>Charles</hi> is their gracious Lord and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne; And that having Gods au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, they prayed that they may faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey him; that God would endue him plenteouſly with heavenly gifts; that he would grant him in health
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170328:34"/> and wealth long to live, ſtrengthen him to vanquiſh and overcome all his enemies, and after this life attain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting joy and felicity. And I am peaſwaded, That if theſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the King, and that of the Houſe of Commons by their Speaker (that <hi>God would ſo unite the hearts of King and People, that they might never be divided,</hi>) had been ſtill uſed, we had not ſeen ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable dayes. But the fulleſt of all and unto which I will add no more authorities, is the poſitive Doctrine of the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed by Act of Parliament, in theſe words,<note place="margin">3 Hom. of obedience. Artic. of Rel. 35. Stat. 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>This is Gods Ordinance, Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and Gods holy will; That the whole body of every Realme, and all the parts and members of the ſame, ſhall be ſubject to their Head, their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though this Law ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally conſented to, and not diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with Right and Juſtice, is a ſufficient ground to cauſe every good man to believe and obey it,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170328:35"/> according to that of the Poet,
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Vir bonus eſt quis?</l>
                  <l>Qui conſulta patrum, leges qui juraque ſervat.</l>
               </q> Yet I will in the next place give ſome Reaſons for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The firſt Reaſon is taken from the nature of this Governement, being Monarchy, The Governement by which God Governs all the world, the government by which the <hi>Sun rules the day;</hi> the governement which God inſtituted in Paradice, when he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Adam,</hi> making him a Man and a King at once, giving him the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over all creatures, eſpecially his own family, in which the Kingſhip continued in him, and the Primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of his Family for <hi>above</hi> 2000 <hi>years;</hi> So that Kingly Government, and that of Families, having their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall together, differ not in nature but in extent (Kingſhip being nothing elſe but an orderly rule over multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed families, under one governour in chief) Now the Law of <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="*" place="margin">34. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.40. 12 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol.</hi> 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Ket. rep. D. &amp; St.</hi> cap. 6.</note> founded on the Law of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170328:35"/> the Soveraigne Power over Subjects like that of families; and therefore the King of <hi>England</hi> is called in our Books of Law,<note place="margin">11 <hi>Rep.</hi> f. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Parens patriae &amp; paterfamilias totius regni;</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all his Subjects, and the whole Kingdome to be but the family, of which he is the Head. And therefore what the bleſſed Apoſtle obſerves of his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I may obſerve the ſame of our <hi>England, We have had</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Fathers of our fleſh correcting us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> (inſtead of reſiſting) <hi>we gave them reverence;</hi> But who ever ſaw children beating their parents, but with horrour and amazement: the like may be ſaid of Subjects fighting, beating, and depoſing their Kings; And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever by the judgement of God, and as a plague upon this Kingdome, ſuch abominable Acts have been done by Parliaments, witneſs thoſe tragick examples of the two ſecond Kings of their name, <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured under a miſhapen form of Law, by two traiterous and perjur'd Judges of the Realme, <hi>Truſſell</hi> and <hi>Thirning,</hi> (the worſt of their name, and the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170328:36"/> ſteine of their profeſſion) yet what became of the prime Actors in that bloudy ſcene, and how God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged the bloud of thoſe Kings upon the whole Kingdome, I referre my Reader to the learned Pen of the moſt famous Hiſtorian of our time,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> W. Raul. Praf.</note> for a large and exact relation of ſo ſad and bad a ſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> My ſecond Reaſon is taken from the regard the Law hath to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Supreame Governour,<note place="margin">11 <hi>Rep.</hi> f 20. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming him the Head of the Law, and the Fountain of Juſtice, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him <hi>Capitalis Juſticiarius toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Angliae;</hi> Now both Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſhould ill provide for the King, if they ſhould leave him to the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and puniſhment of his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; For then it would be impoſſible for him to be ſafe, whether good or bad; Nay good Princes would here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be in the worſt condition. For this being true, that farre the greater part of the people are wicked, and wicked people do naturally hate good Princes, even for their goodneſs, (as <hi>David,</hi> a King and a good King ſpeaks of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170328:36"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.20. <hi>They alſo that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der evill for good are my adverſaries, becauſe I follow the thing that good is,</hi>) it will conſequently follow, that good Princes are in the worſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it ſhould be in the Power of the people to puniſh them. For it hath been found true in all ages, that the beſt of Princes have had the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions againſt them: Infinite exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples might be produced, I ſhall name but two or three. <hi>David</hi> we know was a King after Gods own heart, and yet as good as he was, he was not free from many treaſons and rebellions againſt him; Whereas of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> a moſt wicked and Idolatrous King, and who Raigned much longer, we read not ſo much as of on treaſon or rebellion againſt him all his long Raigne of five and fifty years, My next inſtance ſhall be nearer home; Thoſe two matchleſs Princes for piety and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, children of one Father, King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſcarce a year in either of their Raignes paſſed over their heads without ſome trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, rebellion, or inſurrection, plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170328:37"/> or acted againſt them by their own Subjects. And for this cauſe it is that the Law hath left the King to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the higheſt judge. For if the Subject ſhould judge him, it muſt be by ſome proceſs of Law, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in the Kings name, and it is abſurd to think, that the King can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſue or judge himſelf. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Writ of Aſſize of <hi>Darreyn Praeſentment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fitz. nat. brev. <hi>31. F.</hi>
               </note> which in the caſe of the Subject runnes thus; <hi>Rex Vicecom'.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſalutem, ſi A. fecerit te ſecurum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>tunc ſumon'. per bonos Cummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis,</hi> &amp;c. But in the Kings caſe, the words <hi>ſi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>fecerit te ſecurum,</hi> are left out, in that the King, for the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his perſon, cannot find pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, for then he might be amerced or puniſhed for want of them, which is againſt the nature of royall Majeſty: Beſides how is it poſſible the King ſhould be tri'd, he having no Peers, when all Tryall in Law is <hi>per paeres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bracton.</note> Monarchy and Peers being as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible and inconſiſtent as order and confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> My third Reaſon is taken from the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170328:37"/> nature of the people, impatient of the yoake, and apt to quarrel with governement, be it never ſo good,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Omni enim populo ineſt malignum quiddam &amp; querulum in imperantes:</hi> And therefore it is that the Law of <hi>England</hi> hath exalted the Thrones of Kings above the reach of the people, and ſubmitted them to God: And it is for the benefit and ſafety of the people it ſhould be ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Co. Inſtit.</hi> 1. <hi>part</hi> f. 64.</note> 
               <hi>Imperii maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas eſt tutelae ſalus</hi> (ſaith the Law) the dignity of the Prince is the peoples ſecurity; And ſo it hath fallen out in all ages, that ſo long as the people upheld the Majeſty of the King, ſo long they have been happy; But as ſoon as they forſooke it, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have been cruſht to pieces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fall. So it fell out at <hi>Athens,</hi> one of the moſt flouriſhing Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths in the world: The people weary of the Governement of their hereditary Kings, firſt expelled them, &amp; then ſet up <hi>Decennimicall Governors</hi> in their roomes; After that their <hi>Oly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy</hi> of four hundred Commoners, And after them their <hi>thirty Tyrants,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170328:38"/> who brought their Commonwealth to utter ruine; And thus it was with poore <hi>England</hi> in the dayes of King <hi>John</hi> and King <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. his ſonne, when the Lords and Commons waged warre againſt theſe Princes, aſſumed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of <hi>England</hi> to themſelves, and deputed it into the hands of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four Commiſſioners; took King <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. and <hi>Edward</hi> his ſonne, and kept them Priſoners in <hi>Killingworth</hi> Caſtle for almoſt two years. But what was the iſſue of this glorious miſrule, which laſted firſt and laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt threeſcore years? what good had the people by it? I will tell you in the language of <hi>Tacitus, Auferre tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidare, rapere pro imperio habent, atque ubi ſolitudinem fecerint, hoc pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem appellant;</hi> to rob them, to ſpoile them, to kill them, was all the juſtice they had; And when they were ſtript of all, and their poſſeſſions laid waſte and deſolate, that was accounted there Peace. And what theſe Lords of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule gained by it, the Statute called <hi>Dictum de Killingworth</hi> tells us.<note place="margin">V. M. Chaſt. Anno. <hi>1556. 51.</hi> Hen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> They were all glad to compound with that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170328:38"/> mercifull King for their fines and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, at that very Caſtle where they kept him Priſoner. Hence it came to paſs, that the poore Commoners of <hi>England</hi> (ſo made, by the low and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected ſtate of the Crown, in the dayes of King <hi>Rich.</hi> 2.) joyned with the Lords by Petition in Parliament to the King:<note place="margin">Rot. Par. <hi>14.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> n. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> That the Majeſty and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of his Crown might be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and kept, And that all things done to the contrary might be redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, knowing that mens private eſtates are not ſafe, when the Crown is not ſecure: And therefore the ſpirit of truth commands us in the firſt place to pray for Kings, That under them <hi>we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, that when the Crown is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, no quietneſs, no peace, no godlineſs, no honeſty is to be found in that Kingdome. I will ſhut up this in the obſervation of <hi>Comines,</hi> a great and wiſe Stateſ-man, <hi>That he never knew a man in all his life, that ſought to put in fear, or hold his Prince in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that ever came to good end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170328:39"/>4. Theſe amongſt divers more are the Reaſons of Law in this point, touching the Supremacy of Kings. I come now to the Objections, all of them conſiſting upon diſtinctions, which often argue a galled conſcience, as if conſcience told them this to be true, but were willing to be cheated into errour by a diſtinction, and then it falls out to be true, what was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a judicious Divine,<note place="margin">Hooker <hi>Eccl.</hi> Pol.</note> 
               <hi>That obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience accompanied with unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to obey, is no better than diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Firſt they object, This obedience to Kings is not abſolute, but upon condition, ſo that they governe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The Law of <hi>England</hi> makes no ſuch diſtinction, as I have ſaid and proved before, <hi>Et ubi lex non diſtinguit, nec nos diſtinguere debemus.</hi> Neither could I ever read, that any Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in the world was ſo founded. For as for that of the <hi>Ephori</hi> amongſt the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and the <hi>Demarchy,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly objected, for the power they had
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170328:39"/> of the coerſion of Kings: It is well known, that they were both of them uſurpations, and contrary to the firſt foundation and conſtitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of thoſe famous Cities, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Sparta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they ſay, though the Law have <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> no ſuch expreſs condition, yet it is implyed in this manner; Kings are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the good of the People, and therefore if they rule to their hurt, the people may right themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This is an abſurd conſequence, that ſhakes the foundation of all Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for Paſtors, Husbands, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Maſters, are ordained for the good of their flock, their wives, their children and ſervants, if they diſcharge not their ſeverall duties to all theſe, they by this reaſon may be no longer obeyed by them, And ſo by this means Inferiours ſhall Lord it over Superiours, contrary to the order of Nature, Reaſon, and Law; No, but the Argument holds thus; Paſtors, Husbands, Parents, Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being ordained by God, to governe their flock, their wives, their children,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170328:40"/> and ſervants, in godlineſs and honeſty, ſhall ſeverely anſwer to God for breach of this truſt committed to them by him if they governe amiſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> But Kings are not the Ordinance of God but of men, for it's ſaid 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelf to every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whether to the King as Supream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Many learned Expoſitions are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of this place by very learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hammond</hi> and others. I ſhall for the preſent only content my ſelf with that brief one of <hi>Piſcator,</hi> who expounds it, <hi>Ratione ſubjecti non ratione cauſae,</hi> That is, Kings are ſaid to be the Ordinance of men, as they exerciſe their Authourity amongſt men, not as men are Authors of their Authority, for that only belongs to God; and therefore the King is called <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>the Miniſter of God;</hi> and the words of that Text intimate ſo much, that this ſubjection ſhould be unto Kings, <hi>Dei cauſa, for the Lords ſake,</hi> for only <hi>by him Kings Reigne, Prov.</hi> 8. Like as it is of Miniſters of the Goſpel, they have impoſition of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170328:40"/> hands from men, and preach to men, but their function and authority is from God, and therefore they are called, <hi>Miniſters of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is objected, that the King is not King till he be Crowned, and then at his Coronation he promiſeth by Oath to his people three things, ſaith <hi>Bracton.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Bracton Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Sanf. pl. Cor.</note> To ſee the peace of the Church and people be kept. 2. To repell all force, and keep his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from wrong. 3. That in all his judgements he exerciſe Juſtice and Mercy; Now if he performe not theſe Conditions, the people are free, and not bound to obey.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is neither ſo nor ſo,<note place="margin">C. 7. <hi>Rep. Calvins</hi> caſe.</note> for Kings are abſolute Kings before they be Crowned, for Coronation is not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall to the King, but only orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall: <hi>Edward</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> called his Parliament before he was Crowned, ſo did King <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. call divers, being not Crowned till the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his Raigne; and it was adjudged in the Caſe of the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cok.</hi> 3. Inſt. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.</note> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walter Rawley,</hi> &amp;c. 1. <hi>Jac.</hi> that to conſpire
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170328:41"/> the death of the King before his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation was High-Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Oath he takes at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation to performe thoſe recited promiſes to his people, is not Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, neither doth any clauſe in it ſound like a Condition, unleſs they will have it to be in the concluſion of the Oath, which then alſo makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; for the words are, <hi>Ita me Deus adjuvet,</hi> Let God deal thus and thus with me, if I performe not the Oath made to him: It is not, <hi>Ita me juvet populus,</hi> Let the people do ſo and ſo to me. And the Perjury of Princes is tryed at Gods Barre, not at mans.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> It is confeſſed to be true, that the King is greater than any one ſingle perſon in the Kingdome, but he is not greater than all the people of the Kingdome put together, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a new diſtinction kindled from a new-found-light of <hi>ſingulis major</hi> and <hi>univerſis minor,</hi> infuſed into ſome people, have made them ſwell at this day till they are ready to burſt; which being ſtrictly examined, will prove
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170328:41"/> nothing elſe but <hi>bulla bullata,</hi> a blown bubble, which experience tells us, is nothing till it be blown, and quickly blown into nothing: And therefore I will give it a twofold anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Minor</hi> are terms of quantity, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> as <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> are termes of quality. Now in things of quantity, the diſtinction of <hi>ſingulis major,</hi> and <hi>univerſis minor,</hi> holds true; but not in things of quality, (quantity and quality being of ſeverall natures, and belonging to ſeverall Predicaments,) as for example, a Schoolemaſter of a Schoole is for the moſt part in reſpect of quantity of body greater than any Boy of the Schoole, and leſs than all put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; But that man deſerves to be whipt that will affirme, that in reſpect of power and authority, he is not greater than all the Boyes in the Schoole put together, he having power to correct them, not they him.</p>
            <p>So, and much more may it be ſaid of Kings and Princes, that they are in power and dignity <hi>univerſis majores,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170328:42"/> greater than all the people joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in that the whole people make but one body Politick, of which the King is the Head, and hath as much power and ſuperiority over that Body politick without check or controll, as the head of any man hath over the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, for ſo is the reſemblance of Law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I anſwer, the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy doth not as other Powers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their efficiency from naturall and inferiour Cauſes, for his preferment doth not ſpring from the duſt, but from him who ſtiles himſelf the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks.<note place="margin">Dan. 2.21.</note> And therefore the Kings Authority being from him, it cannot poſſibly be ſubject to any infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magiſtracy which derives it ſelf only from the Prince; for not only all ſingle-Perſons within the Realme, but all Corporate and Repreſentative Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies derive their dignity and power from him, and acknowledg in their entire and univerſall capacities, to owe unto him all humble obedience, as it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170328:42"/> is expreſſed in the Statute of 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c 12.</note> And then it neceſſarily follows accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Maxime in Schooles, <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid efficit tale, illud magis tale,</hi> He that as Head gives power to his Subjects, cannot himſelf be ſubject to that power he gives.</p>
            <p>The ſixth and laſt Objection, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> the moſt Giant-like, from whence all other Objections, like hands from the ſhoulders of <hi>Briareus,</hi> are derived from two new coined diſtinctions from new men, and of a new Mint, <hi>viz.</hi> A Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Power to the King, and a Co-ordinate Power with the King; An actuall power or preſence of the King, and a virtuall power or preſence of the King: and upon theſe two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions the Objection ſtands thus. When the King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons meet in Parliament, they meet as three Eſtates, The King the firſt, the Lords the ſecond, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the third. Theſe three (ſay they) in the paſſing of Bils have a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate power. So that if the Lords and Commons do paſs a Bill, and the King refuſe it, yet it ſhall paſs as a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170328:43"/> Law, by virtue of two Co-ordinate powers againſt the third power, and ſo the King ſhall have no negative voice. And in caſe the King ſhall be abſent from Parliament, whereby he cannot aſſent, then by reaſon of a virtuall power of a King, which in caſe of his abſence is veſted in the two Houſes, the conſent of the two Houſes ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his aſſent, and ſo ſhall paſs as a Law by way of Ordinance: So that in both caſes, the ſcope and drift of the Objection is to exclude the King from having any Negative voice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Admitting this diſtinction to be true (though I can ſhew divers Parliaments which make the King more than a third eſtate,) I ſhall notwithſtanding give this anſwer; That this being an Objection ſo greatly countenanced by men of the Gown, I will not be ſo uncivill, as to ſay it is abſurd, irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and illegall; But I will crave leave to endeavour to prove all theſe three.</p>
            <p>For the firſt; If the King and Lords which (as they ſay) are two the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Eſtates in Parliament, (though in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170328:43"/> truth the King be more than an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) ſhould agree upon a Bill, and the Houſe of Commons ſhould refuſe to agree to it; yet if this ſhould be true, as is objected, then the two Co-ordinate powers (as they ſpeak) of King and Lords aſſenting to the Bill, ſhould over-rule the third, not aſſenting to it, and ſo the Bill ſhould paſs as a Law to bind the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, without the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: Or put the caſe the Houſe of Commons ſhould abſent themſelves, (Speaker and all) as it is not time out of mind that ſuch a caſe hath been, yet the two other Co-ordinate Powers, in this caſe of abſence, might by the like reaſon, by a kind of virtuall power, (I know not from whence) paſs the Bill as a binding Law for the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which how abſurd theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions are from the two former di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, I leave to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> to judg of: <hi>Eadem est lex, ubi par ratio;</hi> nay the reaſon is much ſtronger in the Kings caſe. For if the Lords and Commons which are the leſſer Powers, may exclude the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170328:44"/> Kings negative voice, which is the Supreame Power, much more may the King and Lords being the greateſt Powers, exclude the Commons which is the leaſt. And if ſo, then what need is there of their preſence in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments; And if that, then what need of Parliaments? So endleſs are the abſurdities that follow upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, that ariſe from brainleſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is irrationall; for how can it be thought reaſonable, that the King who hath the ſole right of Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliaments at his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to give him counſell and advice touching thoſe weighty affairs, for which he cals them, ſhould not have liberty to aſſent or diſaſſent to what both Houſes adviſe, be it good or bad? Otherwiſe it will follow, that if they ſhall tender him a Bill for the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Rights of his Crown, which by his Coronation-Oath, he is bound to maintain, or tender him a Bill for his depoſition or dethroning (as they did to thoſe two unfortunate Princes, <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. and <hi>Rich.</hi> 2.) he muſt yield
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170328:44"/> his aſſent to thoſe Bils, in that the concurrence of the two other Co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Powers (as they call them) had taken away his Negative voice. What had become of our Religion at this day, if this had been either Law or Reaſon in the firſt year of the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when the Lords and Commons of that Parliament would never have aboliſhed Popery and the Maſſe, had it been in their Power by Law, to have excluded that religious Queen of her Negative voice? But the Judges of the Realme (though all of them at that time Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected, and) as learned men as any were either before, or ſince, knew no ſuch Law, as by two illegall diſtinctions (as they are applyed) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the Crowne of its moſt ancient Prerogative.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly and chiefly, The two diſtinctions of Co-ordinate and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Power, Actuall and Virtuall Preſence, as they are applied in the Objection, are againſt Law.</p>
            <p>Co-ordination as well in Logick as in Law, are of things of the ſame rank,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170328:45"/> of the ſame dignity, and of the ſame order: As for example, four Judges of the Kings Bench are ſaid to be Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate in Power, becauſe they are men of the ſame rank, of the ſame dignity, of the ſame power; and the like of the four Judges of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas, and the Barrons of the Exchequer. And the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under his own broad-Seale (not any other) which gives them their dignity, is alike to them all. But it is otherwiſe in the high Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the King ſits there as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Power, the Lords ſit beneath his Throne all uncovered before him; the Commons ſtand bare at the Barre; and both of them in all their publick Acts, where they ſpeak of him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves his humble and dutifull Subjects. So likewiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lords Houſe, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe, there is a great difference in point of rank and order. For the Lords Houſe is by divers Acts of Parliament,<note place="margin">33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. cap. 21. Co. 5. rep. 14. <hi>à Crompt.</hi> Juriſd. tit. Parl.</note> and Book-caſes, called the upper, or higher Houſe; The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe is called, the neather or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170328:45"/> lower Houſe. And when theſe Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſend to one another, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſend Members of their own, on the meſſage; the Lords ſend no Members, but only Attendants on their Houſe. No Lord comes to the Commons Houſe, much leſs ſtands at the doore, and waits as the Commons do. And when both Houſes meet at a Conference, the Lords ſit with their Hats on, the Commons ſtand before them with their Hats off, with many more differences of rank and order, diſproving a Co-ordination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which for brevities ſake I omit. The truth is,<note place="margin">☜</note> that in paſſing of Bils there is a joynt concurrent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the King, and two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called a Co-agreement, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Co-aſſent of will, but by no means can it be called a Co-ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, intimating a ſameneſs in rank, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and power.</p>
            <p>For the other diſtinction of actuall and virtuall preſence, or actuall and virtuall power, as it is apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Objection, it is alike
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170328:46"/> illegall, which will thus appeare.</p>
            <p>Before the Statute of 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. never any Bill paſſed in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for a Law (the King being within the Realme) by the Lords and Commons alone, without the Kings perſonall aſſent in Parliament to the Bill, as he that gave life and being to the Law; And therefore their ancient Statutes ran in the Kings name alone, as the principall Agent and efficient in paſſing a Law, as the Statute of <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. though made with the aſſent of Lords and Commons, yet it runs in this forme, <hi>Henricus Dei gratiâ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sciatis quod Nos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitu Dei ad exaltationem Sanctae Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, &amp; emendationem Regni no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, ſpontanea &amp; bona voluntate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra dedimus &amp; conceſsimus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>has libertates ſubſcriptas,</hi> &amp;c. So the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 1. in 3. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. runnes thus;<note place="margin">41. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. 52. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. c. 3. 28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. c. 5. 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ceux ſont le eſtabliſhments, le Roy</hi> Edw. <hi>fitz l' Roy,</hi> Hen. <hi>faits à Weſtminster.</hi> The like is ſaid of the Statute of <hi>York,</hi> 12. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. and many more, which for brevities ſake I have quoted in the Margin.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170328:46"/>
            <p>Neither can any man alive give me one inſtance ſince Parliaments began in <hi>England,</hi> that while the King was within the Realme, in what condition ſoever he was in, that ever any Act or Ordinance of Parliament paſſed as a Law without his perſonall aſſent. I put the caſe of the Kings being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Land. For when he was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to go out of the Land, as <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. into the holy Land, <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. into <hi>France,</hi> they made by their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions a <hi>Cuſtos Regni,</hi> which ſupplied the Kingly office, as <hi>William Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champ</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Eli,</hi> was made <hi>Cuſtos Regni,</hi> to <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. and the reaſon of the Law was plaine in it, for while the King is in <hi>England,</hi> he ought to Act as a King, by perſonall aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Bils, one of the higheſt Acts of Majeſty which he is to enjoy by Law.</p>
            <p>But the Statute of 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.<note place="margin">Stat. 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. cap. 21.</note> made a little alteration of the Law in the manner of paſſing of Bils, which Statute was made at the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, upon their impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170328:47"/> of Queen <hi>Katherine Howard,</hi> (King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. wife) of High-Treaſon, where they humbly beſeech the King, (<hi>for feare trouble ſhould ariſe to his heart, and unquietneſſe to his mind, to the ſhortning of his dayes,</hi> if he ſhould appear in perſon in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and aſſent to the Bill of her At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder,) To grant his Royall Aſſent to the Bill of her Attainder, by his Letters Pattents to be Signed with his own hand, and to be put under his Great Seal, and ſo to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and publiſhed in the Higher Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Higher Houſe (ſo it is there called) to the Lords Spirituall and Temporall and Commons, there to be aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; and ſuch aſſent by the Letters Pattents of the King, is declared to make a perfect Act for the Attainder of that Queen; and that no ſcruple might be made hereof in time to come, concerning this particular, a generall proviſion is there made for all future Parliaments in theſe words following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it declared by Authority of this
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170328:47"/> preſent Parliament, that the Kings Royall aſſent by his Letters Pattents under his Great Seale, and Signed with his hand, and declared and noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his abſence to the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and Temporall, (and to the Commons Aſſembled together) in the higher Houſe, is, and ever was of as good ſtrength and force, as though the Kings perſon had been there perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent, and had aſſented openly and publickly to the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Statute (which I have dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently peruſed) theſe things are very obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That before this Statute, the Kings perſonall and open aſſent to Bils in Parliament, was ſo requiſite that they could not paſs without it; which was the cauſe that made the Lords and Commons in thoſe diſmall Parliaments, in the dayes of thoſe two infortunate Princes, <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. and <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. to require their perſonal aſſent to their own depoſition by Act of Parliament, before they went to execute the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of depoſition againſt them, which they like two weake Princes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170328:48"/> yielded unto, eſpecially the latter, who had he had but a piece of that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-like heart of the firſt of his name,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>King</hi> Rich. <hi>1. called</hi> Ceur de Lyon.</note> he would never have aſſented to an Act of the Renunciation of his own Crown; and not only ſo, but to ſweare to it upon the Goſpell, never to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it in thought, word or deed, (ſo ſaith the Record of that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and after to ſubſcribe to it with his own hand; and further in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of it, pulled a Gold Ring off his finger, (being his Privy-Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net) and put it on the finger of his uſurping Succeſſor, the Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter.</hi> All which things he ſo tame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yielded unto,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 13, 13, 15, 58, 59, 60.</note> and when Chief-Juſtice <hi>Thirning</hi> (too bad a man for ſo good an office) upon that renunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation pronounced the ſentence of depoſition againſt him, the poore King gave him this pittifull anſwer, <hi>That he looked not after rule, but only hoped his Coſen would be a good Lord to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had this virtuall power of paſſing Bils by the two Houſes, without the perſonall aſſent of the King, been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170328:48"/> for currant Law in thoſe dayes. The Judges of thoſe times would not have adviſed <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. to obtain a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall aſſent eſpecially of an impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And therefore the vanity of this virtuall power was well diſcerned by the Lords and Commons in that Parliament of 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this; That becauſe it was not thought convenient the King ſhould perſonally aſſent in Parliament to the Attainder of his own Queen, yet they deviſed a way by that Act, whereby in ſubſtance he ſhould do (in effect) the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame thing; for by his Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents he was to aſſent to the Bill, and that virtuall aſſent was to be Signed with his own hand, and the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners appointed by the Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to ſignifie his aſſent to the Bill, were to notifie it to the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in the Higher Houſe, not as their own, but as the Kings aſſent. What needed all this adoe and caution, if this new device of the virtuall Power in the two Houſes would have ſerved the turne.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170328:49"/>2. The ſecond thing obſervable in this Act of 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. is this, that the manner of aſſent to Bils by the Kings Letters Patents, ſeemed by that Act to be a doubt and ambiguity to the Lords and Commons, who thought that after-ages might confirme it ſo; And therefore they made a generall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by that Act, that for all time to come, the Kings Royall aſſent to Bils, by his Letters Patents Signed with his hand, and notified by his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to the Lords and Commons, ſhould be of as good force and ſtrength as if the King had perſonally appeared in Parliament, and openly aſſented: Which ſtrongly implies, that out of thoſe two caſes, no Bill in Parliament could paſs by the Kings aſſent. From whence then ſhould this virtuall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and preſence proceed, when neither given to the Houſes by the King, nor created by Law, it is not eaſie to be imagined, unleſs from ſome turbulent brain, like that of a Monoſyllable Judge in the dayes of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. (the worſt kind of Judge, when op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Crown) called Judge
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170328:49"/> 
               <hi>Inge,</hi> who delivered it for Law, that the Lords of the upper Houſe without the King and Commons might make Ordinances, diſplace offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had a joynt regiment with the King, in the Government of the Kingdome; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which opinions notwithſtanding his great skill in the Law, he obtained among the Commons no other reputation, than of a learned Traytor.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing obſervable is this, That as it is a juſt priviledge of the Lords and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to aſſent or diſaſſent to Bils in Parliament, though never ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to the Commonwealth, ſo it is likewiſe an undoubted prerogative in the King, being the Higheſt Eſtate in Parliament to have that power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg. And therefore the Lords and Commons do in that Parliament hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire the King, that for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire love and affection he beareth to the Common-wealth, for the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his own Majeſty, and for the peace and unity of all his Subjects, he would paſs that Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which plainly ſheweth, that the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170328:50"/> King had a negative voice as well as they, and might aſſent or diſaſſent at his pleaſure, and an undoubted right of his Crown, as might be proved by infinite examples in all times.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt thing obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in that Act is this, That when an Act is paſſed by both Houſes of Parliament, yet it is not perfect, nor can be put in execution as a Law, till after the Kings royall aſſent, and ſo is the expreſſion of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in that Act of Parliament, <hi>That his Majeſty would grant his royall aſſent to that Act, that ſo after that, it might stand as a perfect Act, and be put in due execution accordingly.</hi> And ſo was the Law ever taken by thoſe two famous Lawyers and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament men, the Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Plowden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plow. <hi>fol.</hi> 79. <hi>Co. Com. Lit.</hi> fol 90.</note> in their learned writings of the Law. But concerning this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voice of the King, I ſhall have occaſion to reſerve it hereafter for a longer diſcourſe, concerning the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Eſtates in Parliament, what belongs to the King as he is King, and the Supreame Eſtate in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; What belongs to the Lords cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170328:50"/> in ſundry Acts of Parliament, the Higher Houſe and what belongs to the Commons called in theſe Acts the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Houſe, a work not done by any, and yet not much difficult to be done But I cannot yet performe it, till I can reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe Notes and Collections I have made out of divers Records of Parliaments, which are now by theſe unhappy times devided from me, and I from them.</p>
            <p>And thus have I endeavoured to anſwer the main Objections againſt this Soveraigne Power of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and cleared it from the Diſloyall aſperſions of undutifull men; And therefore ſhall now in the next place handle the exerciſe of this Soveraigne Power in the two laſt Concluſions, and ſo make an end.</p>
            <p>The fifth Concluſion is this, That <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>5</label> this Soveraigne Power is given to the King, as well for the preſervation of himſelf, as for the governement of his People in Peace and ſafety, for the performance whereof the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> doth furniſh him with the power
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170328:51"/> of the Sword, and annexeth to his Crown the Soveraigne Command of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and therefore he is by our Law called, the chief Captain of all Chivalry within his Dominions. This unqueſtionable Prerogative of the Crown,<note place="margin">Plow. <hi>Com.</hi> fol. 268. <hi>a.</hi>
               </note> I could prove by many Arguments derived from the Law of God, the Law of nature and reaſon, the Law of Nations, and moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly from the Imperiall Laws, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into a compleat Body by <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> out of a vaſt confuſed heap of former Laws. From theſe Laws doth the common Law of <hi>England</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row many grounds of Law, in ſo much that in divers things a man cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the depth of the Laws of <hi>England</hi> without ſome inſight and knowledge in the Civil Law; and it is well known, that our ancient Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſuch as <hi>Glanvill, Bracton, Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> &amp;c. were well ſtudied in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Law. But I intend a compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcourſe, and not a volume, and therefore ſhall prove this point ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently by the common Law without the help of any Ground or Maxime
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170328:51"/> taken from the former Laws, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch as are incorporate into the common Law of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the very beginning and in the very firſt words of <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, (an exact Compendium of the fifty Books of his <hi>Pandects</hi>) it is thus ſaid, <hi>Imperatoriam majeſtatem non ſolum armis decoratam ſed etiam le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus opus eſſe armatam: ut utrumque tempus &amp; bellorum &amp; pacis recte poſsit guhernari;</hi> This Text of the Civill Law is admitted by Chief Juſtice <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſcue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Laud. Leg. Aug</hi> cap. 1. fol. 4.</note> to belong by the common Law to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore as to the firſt part concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Militia,</hi> I will firſt prove it by ancient and ſound authourities in Law. 2. By many Acts of Parliament. And 3. I will give the Reaſons of the Law in both, and ſo conclude this fifth Propoſition, reſerving the latter part concerning the Laws in the ſixt and laſt Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Chief Juſtice <hi>Glanvile</hi>
               <note place="margin">Glanvil in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lego.</note> in his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Book of Law, Written in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. hath theſe words; <hi>Regiam Majeſtatem non ſolum armis contra
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170328:52"/> rebelles &amp; gentes ſibi regnoque inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes oportet eſſe decoratam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reg. Ma. in Praef.</note> 
               <hi>ſed &amp; legibus ad ſubditos &amp; populos pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè regendos decet eſſe ornatam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regia Majeſtas,</hi> A learned Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Law Written at the ſame time thus ſaith; <hi>Regi duo ſunt neceſſaria, Arma quibus hoſtes debellet, leges quibus ſubditos pacificè regat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> in Princip.</note>
               <hi>Bracton,</hi> A learned Judge of the Land, in the dayes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. thus Writeth; <hi>In Rege qui recte regit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsaria ſunt duo haec,</hi> viz. <hi>Arma &amp; Leges;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cat. br.</hi> fol. 113.</note> 
               <hi>quibus utrumque tempus bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, &amp; pacis recte poſsit guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Natura brevium,</hi> A Book of high eſteem in our Law, layeth down this for a Ground, <hi>Et eſt à entendre que le roy, doit de droit ſauver &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender ſon Reaume vers la mere comme vers enemyes, q' il ne ſoit ſurround, ou degaſte &amp; de provider remedy pur ceo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cook.</hi> 2. Rep.</note> 
               <hi>It is to be underſtood,</hi> (ſaith that Book) <hi>that the King ought of Right to ſave and defend his Realm, as well againſt the Sea, as against ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that it be not ſurrounded and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170328:52"/> ſpoiled, and to provide remedy for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is likewiſe reſolved for Law in <hi>Wiſemans</hi> caſe, that to give Land to the King in conſideration that he is head of the Commonwealth, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his people in Peace, and repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the enemies of it, is no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Law to raiſe a uſe; becauſe the King by his Office ought to do all this. And the reaſon of all theſe Authorities is upon this ground. The Law which truſteth the King with the end, <hi>viz.</hi> the preſervation of his people in Warre and Peace, truſteth him with the means to do it, <hi>viz.</hi> Armes and Laws. Many more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities might be cited, which for brevity I omit, and come in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place to the Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And the firſt and moſt ancient is that Law of King <hi>Canutus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inter leges</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuti. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Cook</hi> 2 Inſtit. <hi>fol.</hi> 701. <hi>Lamb.</hi> 135. <hi>Cook.</hi> 1. Inſtit. <hi>fol.</hi> 75.</note> which was before the Conqueſt; <hi>Qui pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem ad oppida ponteſve reficiendos denegabit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Militiamve ſubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfugerit, dabit Regi ſi Anglus fuerit</hi> 26 <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidos;</hi> where it appears, that the Subject was bound as well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170328:53"/> to the Kings <hi>Militia</hi> (for that is the word there uſed) as he was to contribute to the repair of high-wayes and Bridges; which ſtrongly inferres, That the King hath as much Soverign Power over the <hi>Militia</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as he hath over high-wayes and Bridges.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Laws of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Confeſſour, it is thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in theſe words: <hi>Debent enim univerſi liberi homines ſecundum feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſuum &amp; ſecundum tenementa ſua arma habere, &amp; illa ſemper prompta conſervare ad tuitionem Regni &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium Dominorum ſuorum juxta prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum Domini Regis explendum &amp; peragendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that Law in theſe words: <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuimus &amp; firmiter praecipimus, ut omnes comites, &amp; Barones, &amp; Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſervientes, &amp; univerſi liberi homines totius regni noſtri praedicti habeant &amp; teneant ſe ſemper in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, &amp; in equis ut decet &amp; oportet, &amp; quod ſint ſemper prompti &amp; para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ad ſervitium ſuum integrum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plendum
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170328:53"/> &amp; peragendum cum ſemper opus adfuerit ſecundum quod nobis debent de feudis &amp; tenementis ſuis de jure facere,</hi> &amp;c. By both which Laws it plainly appears; That all Earls, Barons, Knights, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England,</hi> (and ſuch were all thoſe that were not villains, Sock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or Copy-holders) were to be in armes upon the Command of the King, and defence of his Kingdom (for ſo he calls it, becauſe King and Kingdom are Relatives, and that man that loves not the one loves not the other, let his pretence be what it will) And not only ſuch Freemen that held their Lands by bearing arms, but all others, as the exigence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhould require, which appears in this, That the King before the Statute of <hi>Quia Emplores terrarum in</hi> 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Litt. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Cook.</hi> Inſtit. <hi>fol.</hi> 75.</note> might create tenures by bearing of Arms; nay more, by creating the greateſt Officers of Arms in the Kingdom, as to be Marſhal of the Kings Hoſt, to be high Conſtable of <hi>England,</hi> and Earl Marſhall of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. By which means it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170328:54"/> grew to be a uſage and cuſtom in the Crown of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">30. <hi>Octob.</hi> 7. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.</note> to have the ſole command of the <hi>Militia</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as appears plainly by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 7. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. where it was agreed by the <hi>Prelates, Earls,</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> and <hi>Commonalty of that Parliament held at Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it was the Kings right, and belonged to him of his Royal Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, to defend all force of Armour, and all other Force againſt the Peace, at all times when it ſhall pleaſe him, and to puniſh them which ſhall do the contrary according to the Laws and uſages of the Realme; And hereunto the people are bound to aid the King as their Sovereign Lord at all ſeaſons, when need ſhould be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, to ſhew his chief Power and Command in this matter of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> given to him by the ancient Laws and Statutes of this Realm, about ſix years after, <hi>viz.</hi> in the 13. year of his Reign, doth by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Winchester</hi> provide in this manner, <hi>That every man ſhall have
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170328:54"/> Harnes in his houſe to keep the Peace according to the ancient aſſeſſe.</hi> That ancient aſſeſſe is thus explained,<note place="margin">Stat. de Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, <hi>13.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that is to ſay, <hi>Every man from fifteene years old to fourty, ſhall be aſſeſſed and ſworne to armour according to their quantity of Lands and Goods, to wit, from fifteen pound Lands, and fourty marks goods a Halbert, a Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of iron, a ſword, a knife, and a horſe: and from ten pound Lands, and twenty marks Goods, a Halbert, a Breſt-plate of Iron, a ſword and a knife: and from fourty ſhillings Land to an hundred ſhillings of Land, a a Sword, a Bowe and arrows, and a knife,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo downward, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more at large in that Statute: Wherein it is likewiſe provided, that two Conſtables in all hundreds ſhould be choſen (now called high Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles) for this purpoſe, that twice every year they ſhould take view of the Armour, and preſent to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſuch defaults about Armour, as they ſhould ſee in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </hi> &amp; <hi>5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Phil. &amp; Mar. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that at the Parliament of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170328:55"/> 4, 5. <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mar.</hi> this Statute was repealed, not as to the power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Arms, but as to the Quantity and proportion of Arms, (the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Arms being at that time chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the value of Lands increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whereby a greater proportion was aſſeſſed) this may appear by the third Chapter of that Parliament, where the power of muſtering of men, and levying a number of them for the Kings ſervice in his warres, is placed wholly in the Crown. And therefore that Statute of Repeal is warily penned, for it is not a repeal of the common Law concerning Arms, but of ſuch Statutes only as concern the keeping and finding of Horſe, horſes, or Armour: which Statute of Repeal was afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed by King <hi>James,</hi> ſo that it neceſſarily followeth, that either the Statute of <hi>Winchester</hi> is ſtill in force, and ſtandeth for Law, or elſe if it be repealed, the common Law of <hi>England</hi> concerning finding of Arms, is in force at this day. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Statutes there are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170328:55"/> this Royal Prerogative of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> in the times of the ſucceeding Kings between <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and Q. <hi>Mar.</hi> eſpecially in the days of <hi>E.</hi> 3. a martial Prince, and a great Souldier, which for the great number of them I ſhall omit, and come in the laſt place to conſider the reaſons of the Law in thus placing the chief power of the <hi>Militia</hi> in the Crown.</p>
            <p>And the firſt Reaſon is taken from the Office and Duty of a King, mentioned by <hi>Plowden</hi> in the caſe of the Information for Mines; where it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Plow. <hi>Com. fol.</hi> 315. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the King is the Head of the Commonwealth, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are his Members, and the Kings Office to which he is appointed by Law, conſiſteth in two things; to wit, in Armour to defend them againſt all hoſtility, and in good Laws.</hi> And therefore it is that <hi>Lipſius</hi> makes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Prudence a neceſſary requiſite for a Prince for the defence of his own Perſon, his Crown and people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> lib. Pol. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> which would not be ſo neceſſary, if the power of the Sword did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and peculiarly belong unto him. And therefore thus is laid
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170328:56"/> down by him, <hi>Toloſanus, Bodine,</hi> and <hi>Bozerus</hi> (famous and learned Politicians) as a maxim moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to royal Majeſty, <hi>Solius eſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis bellum ſuſcipere, decernere, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; adminiſtrare.</hi> It is only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to a Prince to denounce Warre, to undertake it, to order and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, which they largely prove; I ſhall only but quote the places in the Margin.<note place="margin">Toloſ. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Bod. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. <hi>de Jur. Belli c.</hi> 4. Lipſius <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Cook.</hi> 3. Inſtit. <hi>fol.</hi> 9.</note> And agreeable to this is the Law of <hi>England;</hi> No Subject ſaith Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> (an Authour of an approved Authority) no Parliament, can levy Warre within the Realm without Authority from the King, for to him, ſaith he, it only belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And therefore he puts theſe caſes, That if Subjects (in the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral number) ſhall levy Warre to expulſe ſtrangers, to deliver men out of priſons, to remove Counſellours, or againſt any Statute, or to any other end, pretending Reformation of their own heads, without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, they are (his own words) ſaith he, a levying of Warre againſt the King. And hereupon it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170328:56"/> for Law in the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th,<note place="margin">19. E. 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 6. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> That if the King of <hi>England</hi> do make a league with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and all the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> will make War againſt thoſe of <hi>Denmark,</hi> if the King of <hi>England</hi> aſſent not to it; It ſhall not be accounted a Warre. For none in <hi>England</hi> can raiſe Warre, but by Authority from the King, as was ſaid before.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon is drawn from the Office and Duty of Subjects, which is to be obedient to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to fear and honour their Princes. It is the ſpeech of God from the Law of Nature,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>If I be a Father, where is my honour? and if I be a Maſter, where is my fear?</hi> Kings are both, and therefore ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fear do naturally belong to them. And can the King have either, if the Sword ſhould not be in his hand? It is the very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apoſtle, to perſwade Subjects to <hi>be afraid of committing evil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the King beareth not the Sword in vain, but is Gods miniſter,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170328:57"/> to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi> A King without a Sword is like a Father without a rod, the child incorrigible, the Subject rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious. The true duty of Obedience to a Prince, is a ſweet mixture of fear and love; they are loved for their mercy, they are feared for their Juſtice, of which the Sword is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Enſign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smite the Shepherd, and the ſheep will be ſcattered.</hi> Kings are ſmitten, when they are deprived of their Swords; and we have ſeen the ſad experience of it with our eyes. Since our Shepherd hath loſt his Sword, what a ſcattering there hath been of all his people, of all ſorts, of all Countreys, of all Cities, Towns and Families, breach upon breach, worſe than that ſcattering in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when there <hi>was no King:</hi> And which will never be happily pieced again, till the people be reduced to their obedience, and the King reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his honour.</p>
            <p>Fire we know, when it is held from aſcending to its proper Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170328:57"/> by the obſtinacy of a thick Cloud, how it rends the Heavens in pieces by horrible thundering and roaring: Such is military power with-held by the Subject from the Crown, till it return thither again, it cauſeth the pillars of a Kingdom to ſhake and tremble: It turns Law into Luſt, Juſtice into Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Kindneſs into Cruelty, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty into Slavery, and a well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Commonwealth into a rude diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Camp.</p>
            <p>My third and laſt reaſon is taken from the conſtitution of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>The world (of which all orderly Republicks, are but ſo many hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome pieces) is named in Gteek Κόσμος, ſignifying Order and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the obedience of Heaven and Earth to that Law of Nature God hath ſet them in the ſtay of the whole world, and makes it at this day ſo lovely and beautifull: <hi>For ſhould the Sunne and Moone wander from their beaten wayes</hi> (as a Reverend Divine elegantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170328:58"/> it) <hi>the times and ſeaſons of the year blend themſelves by a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and confuſed mixture the winds breath out their laſt gaſpe, the Clouds yeeld no rain, the earth be defeated of heavenly influence, the fruits of the Earth pine away as Children at the withered Breſts of their Mother; what would become of man, whom theſe things now do all ſerve?</hi> The like I ſay in a Commonwealth. If Kings ſhould yield up their Crowns unto their Subjects, whereby Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould ride on Horſeback, and Princes walk like Servants on the ground, which muſt needs ſo come to paſſe, if the Chivalry ſhould be in the people, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and deformity ſhould we then behold in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? It would be as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and ugly a ſight in that Politique Body, as in the Body Naturall; To ſee the Head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Foot, and the Foot the Head, from whence Anarchy and Deſolation muſt needs follow, when the King by this means ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170328:58"/> the only Subject in the Land.</p>
            <p>Many more reaſons may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but theſe ſhall ſuffice, and I ſhall in the next place handle the ſecond weapon of the Crown, by which the People of the Realme is governed in the time of Peace, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lawes of the Land, by diſcuſſing the ſixth and laſt concluſion, which is this.</p>
            <p>That this Kingly Government be according to the Law of the Land, not by the Laws of luſt, but by the Laws of the Land; by legal, not by arbitrary power; and this makes the King of <hi>England</hi> the greateſt and moſt compleat Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in the world. That the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is incorporated, and interwoven with the Laws of the Land. For it is the groſſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of thoſe men, that make Monarchy to conſiſt in Exemption from Laws; ſuch a Monarchy is rather to be called Diſſolute, than Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; Impotent, than Powerfull;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170328:59"/> Tyrannical, than Regal. I have many learned Authours to warrant this; I will only inſtance in three, <hi>Rex</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bracton</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bracton l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9</hi>
               </note>) <hi>dicitur à bene regendo, non à regnando; quia Rex eſt dum bene gerit, Tyrannus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dum Populum ſibi concreditum violenta opprimit Dominatione,</hi> ſaith Sir <hi>Jo. Forteſcue. Ch. Juſt. of Engl.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Forteſ. de laud. leg. Ang. c. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quis enim (Rex) potentior li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beriorve eſſe poteſt quam qui non ſolum alios, ſed &amp; ſeipſum ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit debellare; quod poteſt, &amp; ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per facit Rex politice regens populum ſuum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all is the Teſtimony of King <hi>James,</hi> as great a Prince in Learning, as in Power; <hi>A King,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>governing in a ſetled Kingdome, leaves off to be a King, and degenerates into a Tyrant, as ſoone as he leaves off to rule accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Lawes. Therefore all Kings that are not Tyrants, or perjured, will be glad to bound themſelves within the limits of their Lawes, and they that perſwade
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170328:59"/> them the contrary, are vipers and Peſts both againſt them, and the Commonwealth.</hi> And afterward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to the Lords and Commons his opinion of the Common Laws by which his Realme was governed he thus ſpeaketh, <hi>Firſt as a King I have beaſt cauſe of any man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Common Law. For no Laws can be more advantagious for a King, and extendeth further his Praeroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive than it doth. And for a King of</hi> England <hi>to deſpiſe the Common Law, it is to neglect his own Crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how apt and convenient a Law it is for the people as well as for the Crown, he expreſſeth it in another ſpeech to the Parliament, <hi>I muſt needs confeſſe, and I think I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove it, that the grounds of the Common Law of</hi> England <hi>are the beſt of any Law in the world, either civill or municipall, and the fitteſt for this people.</hi> Upon all which it plainly appears, as I ſaid before, that a King of <hi>England</hi> governing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Laws, is the moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170328:60"/> and free Monarch of the world; For this is true freedome in a Prince, to be loved at home, and feared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, to be able to defend his own people at home from oppreſſion and violence by his Laws, without the help of an Army; to keep and conſerve all his Subjects in happy peace, by a ſword made of Parchment and Paper in his Laws, and not by a Sword made up of Iron and Steel in his Armies. This is excellently and at large declared by the ſame S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Forteſcue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 35, 36, 37.</note> in his book of the praiſe of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> where in three ſeverall Chapters he ſets down the differences betwixt the Engliſh Governement by the Laws, and the other Governement by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power (miſnamed Regall Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) and there makes the Compariſon betwixt the Governement of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that of <hi>France; That they are poor Peaſants, we a rich people; They are ſo pilled and polled with Taxes and Impoſitions (eſpecially that of Salt) that they are not able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their King, if he ſhould need their ſuccour, we are able to ſuccour him
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170328:60"/> in Warre, and to relieve him in want; No Souldiers (in time of peace) can come by Law into our Houſes, ſpoile our Goods, and eat us out with Free-Quarter as they do there; Nor are we privily executed by Martiall Law, without open and ordinary Juſtice as they are,</hi> with many more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances which he there relateth at large, and unto which I referre my Reader. So that no Nation under Heaven is more happy under Kingly Governement, than we are here in <hi>England,</hi> were we a thankfull people, or rightly prized our own happineſſe, For the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is ſo encir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled with good Laws, that it is ſcarce poſſible for a King of <hi>England</hi> to fall into Tyranny,<note place="margin">8. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.19. 8. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.20. 2. <hi>Rich.</hi> 3.11.</note> for he neither ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, nor acteth, nor judgeth, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuteth, but by his Writt, by his Laws, by his Judges, and Miniſters, and both theſe ſworne to him to judge a right, and to execute juſtice to his People. For the King doth nothing in his own Perſon.<note place="margin">Forteſ. de de Land <hi>Leg. cap. 8.</hi>
               </note> If he ſit in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as he may do in any of his Courts, as King <hi>Richard</hi> 2. King
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170328:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> 4. and King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. did in the Kings-Bench, King <hi>Henry</hi> 7. and King <hi>James</hi> in the Starre-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet he pronounceth <hi rend="strikethrough">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <add>not</add> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment himſelf upon his People, but it is left by him to the proper Judges of that Court under him, which is the reaſon why it is ſaid in our Law, that <hi>the King can do no wrong;</hi> for if the Subject here in <hi>England</hi> be wronged, it is by ſome Judge, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, or Miniſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the King which hath wronged him, and for which the Subject may have his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per remedy in Law, in which juſtice cannot be denied him, or delayed by the Judges,<note place="margin">9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. c. 29. 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. c. 9.</note> who are required by their duty and Oath, not to ſtay or ſtop Juſtice,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. c. 8.</note> either for the Great Seale or Little Seale, which are the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Commands of the King. The words of the Statute are more Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall, <hi>Item, It is Accorded and Eſtabliſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. Oath of the Juſtice.</note> 
               <hi>that it ſhall not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Great Seale, nor the Little Seale, to diſturbe or delay Common Right; And though ſuch commandment do come, the Juſtices
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170328:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> therefore ſhall not leave to do right in any point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all the Statute of 20. <hi>Edward</hi> 3. is remarkeable, which hath theſe words, <hi>We Command all Our Justices that they ſhall from henceforth do equall Law and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right to all Our Subjects rich and poor, without having regard to any perſon, and without omitting to do Right for any Letters or Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may come to them from us, or from any other, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cauſe.</hi> Let the Judges do right, and the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as they can do no wrong; ſo are not they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do it, as may appear in the examples of King <hi>James</hi> and the King that now is, <hi rend="strikethrough">T</hi>
               <add>W</add>hen I was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter in the Common-Pleas about 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Jac.</hi> There happened in that Court a Suit in a <hi>Quare Impedit,</hi> Between S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Pincheon,</hi> and one <hi>Harris</hi> the Kings Incumbent, which Suit after a long and tedious delay in Chancery, came at laſt to receive a Judgement, in the Court of Common-Pleas; At the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170328:62"/> for giving of Judgement, The Lord <hi>Hubert</hi> Chief Juſtice of that Court, produced a Letter out of his Pocket from King <hi>James,</hi> for deferring Judgement, which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the reſt of the Judges of that Court, <hi>Warburton, Winch,</hi> and <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colls,</hi> deſiring their Advice what to do: Juſtice <hi>Nicolls</hi> Puiſne Judge of the Court, and firſt to Argue, ſpake openly in this manner; <hi>My Lord, This Cauſe hath had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny delaies, It is our duty to do equal right to all his Majeſties Subjects, and that we ought not to delay Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, neither for the Great Seale, nor the Little, and much leſſe for a Letter; And therefore for my part I will go on and proceed to Judgment,</hi> which he then gave for Sr. <hi>Edward Pincheon,</hi> and the reſt of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es followed according to their turns and did the like. How this wrought with King <hi>James</hi> the Conſequence will ſhew. For about a year after, when Officers were to be choſen for the Prince his Sonne, the King that now is, then newly made Prince
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170328:62"/> of <hi>Wales,</hi> The Higheſt Office being the Office of Chancellour, had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe great Competitors, the Lord <hi>Hubert,</hi> and Sr. <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> then Atturnay Generall and ſome others. The King rejected them all, and of himſelfe choſe Juſtice <hi>Nicholls,</hi> that neither ſought it, or thought of it, ſixty miles off at his houſe in the Countrey, being in the long Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and I was ſent for from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to convey his Patent to him into the Countrey, which I did accordingly; and about a Moneth after, going up at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, he was preſented to the King, who ſcarce ever ſaw him before. The King told him, <hi>That he took notice of him for an honeſt and a just Judge, and one that would take no Bribes, and therefore had made choice of him to ſerve his Sonne in his Highest Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The like I have heard of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that now is, by another Judg a Succeſſor of his in the ſame Court of Common Pleas, who did Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Juſtice notwithſtanding the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170328:63"/> Kings Letter, whereupon he was ſent for to the King, who grew angry with him for doing contrary to his Letter; The Judge acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with that high command that was laid upon him by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> 3, to do equall Law and Execution of Right to all his Majeſties Subjects, and by his Oath to the King to performe it; telling his Majeſty, <hi>That his Throne was eſtabliſhed by executing Juſtice, and much Honour redounded to him thereby,</hi> and many other words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in better Languge than I am able to expreſſe, whereupon the Kings heart began to melt, telling the Judge he was well pleaſed with him, and bade him go on in the wayes of Law and Juſtice, and he ſhould have his favour in ſtead of his frowne. And hereupon I heard the Judge deliver this opinion of him. <hi>That he thought he would make the juſteſt Prince upon Earth, had he Miniſters about him anſwerable to his goodneſſe.</hi> Thus are good Kings ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er brought to ſed their Errours in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170328:63"/> the quiet and ſtill wayes of Juſtice grounded upon the ſincerity of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Laws, than by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of publique Perſons, when they are proſecuted in a violent way. And ſuch a naturall Inclination to the love of Juſtice doth poſſeſſe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Princes, that they ſeldome miſcarry in their duties, did not their Miniſters under them, whom they entruſt with their Laws, firſt fayle in theirs. And therefore I do affirme and maintaine, that ſince the bloudy contentions about <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> which were begun and continued in the Raignes of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> 3, and happily quieted by King <hi>Edward</hi> 1, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed his Captive Father out of Priſon, vanquiſhed the rebellious Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and confirmed the great Charter, the Oppreſſions of the People of <hi>England,</hi> have been chiefly cauſed by their fellow Subjects, not by their Princes. And therefore the Armes taken up againſt them for that cauſe were utterly groundleſs and unlawfull, as were the Arms taken up againſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170328:64"/> thoſe lawfull, but very infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Princes <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> 2. which brought on their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and Murther afterwards (the moſt traiterous and bloody acts that ever were committed by <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> againſt their Soverign) none of which acts do the known and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Laws of <hi>England</hi> allow, in Subjects againſt their own lawfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns.</p>
            <p>A ſhort touch of which Laws, joyned with an expreſſion of the form of their Oaths, taken at their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, (not commonly known, and leſſe underſtood by the People) I will in the next place handle, and ſo end this my ſixth and laſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. The whole frame and Body of the Common Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is aptly divided into theſe two parts:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Jus Regium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Jus Populi.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Law which concerns the King, being an eſſential part of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170328:64"/> Common Law, the Subject of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is bound by his Allegiance and Oath to obſerve and keep, as ſtrictly and exactly, as that Law which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns himſelf, which every religious and conſcientious Subject will readily do. For I do not find in all the Book of God a more certain mark of an irreligious man, than a deſpiſer of the juſt Government and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of his Sovereign.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Law which concerns the People being another eſſential part of the Common Law, the King of <hi>England</hi> is tied by his Oath at his Coronation, as much to maintain, defend and keep, as he is the Rights of his Crown. So that the Law makes a Marriage between theſe two Rights, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Prince, as of the People.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jus Regium</hi> belonging to the King is divided into
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Jus Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Jus Praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativae.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jus Majeſtatis</hi> is that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to him as King, common to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170328:65"/> him, with other Princes, by the Law of Nature and Nations; as for example, to have the Supream Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in making Laws, the chief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Militia,</hi> by which he beſtows the Degrees of Knighthood, the coyning of Money, the giving of Honour, the pardoning of Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the ſole making and diſpoſing of the Great Seale, the diſpenſing with penall Lawes, the making of Judges and Officers, with divers more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jus Praerogativae,</hi> is that which belongs to him as King of <hi>England,</hi> and given to him by that Law alone, which is very large, and of which the Statute <hi>De Praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativa Regis</hi> made 17<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 2. is but a piece.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jus Populi</hi> is that, which by the ſame Common Law belongs to the People, divided into two parts, Clergy and Laity; the one called <hi>Jus Eccleſiae,</hi> the other called <hi>Jus Regni,</hi> and ſo diſtinguiſhed in the Parliament Writ. Theſe two Rights of King and People make up the Body of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170328:65"/> the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> chiefly conſiſting in Cuſtomes, Liberties, Priviledges and Immunities belonging to Prince and People, and by them approved of, as good and profitable to both, by an immemorial preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, which maketh the beſt Law of all, as moſt fixed and immutable. For other Laws which are not ſo tried by long tract of time, are much ſubject to change and fluctuation, which is the reaſon why the Laws of <hi>England</hi> have at this day the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour above others, in that they conſiſt upon ſuch ancient and unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Principles. But this is a great miſery which hath befallen this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and which we feel at this day, that the People of <hi>England</hi> have been very induſtrious, to know their own Rights, but are very ignorant in the Rights of the Crown. Though by their Oath ſet down in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 1. <hi>Elizab.</hi> they are bound to know them in what they ſwear, <hi>That they ſhall to their Power aſsiſt and defend all Priviledges, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies and Authorities granted, or
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170328:66"/> belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, his Heirs and Succeſſours, or united and annexed to the Imperial Crowne of this Realme.</hi> The ignorance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hath, I fear, to the crying ſinnes of this Land, added the Luod cries of Perjury and Rebellion. And herein thoſe of our own Profeſſion are not without blame, in that I find many Tracts of Law, touching the full Rights of the People; but not one compleat Treatiſe of the whole Prerogative of the King. One Judge <hi>Stanford</hi> hath learnedly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon the Statute of <hi>Praerogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae Regis,</hi> made and enacted 17<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Edward</hi> 2. conſiſting chiefly in Wardſhips and Tenures; but what is that to the large Prerogatvie of the King, extending to other things? Had that been well done, things had not been ſo ill done at this day.</p>
            <p>The Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> as well thoſe which concern the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, as thoſe that concern the People, are both of them ſo united to the Crown, that the one cannot
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170328:66"/> be without the other: inſomuch as the ſafety of the one, is the ſafety of the other; and the hurt of the one, is the hurt of the other: of which many inſtances might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſome of them not written in Ink, but in Blood; whereby a man would think it impoſſible for a King of <hi>England</hi> to govern other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than by his Laws. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for preventing that poſſibility, and all jealouſies and feares touching the ſame, the King takes a ſolemne Oath at his Coronation to maintain them all, which I will ſet down <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim,</hi> as it is to be found in an old A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Statutes of <hi>H.</hi> 8. in theſe words,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THat he ſhall keep and maintaine the Rights and Liberties of the Holy Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oath.</note> 
               <hi>of old time granted by the righteous Chriſtian Kings of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: <hi>And that he ſhall keep all the Lands, Honours and Dignities righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and free of the Crowne of</hi> England, <hi>in all manner whole, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of miniſhment. And
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170328:67"/> the Rights of the Crowne, hurt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, and lost, to his power ſhall call againe into the ancient Eſtate: And that he ſhall keep the Peace of the Holy Church, and of the Clergie, and of the People with good accord. And that he ſhall do in all his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Equity and Right, Justice with Diſcretion and Mercy. And that he ſhall grant to hold the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Realme, and to his power keepe and affirme them, which the Folke and People have made and choſen: And the evil Lawes and Cuſtomes wholly to put out: And ſtedfast and ſtable Peace to the People of this Realme keepe, and cauſe to be kept to his power. And that he ſhall grant no Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but where he may doe it by his Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which theſe things are ſhortly obſervable,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the King ought by his Oath, under the pain of Perjury, to maintain the Rights of his Crown, as well in time of Warre by his Sword,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170328:67"/> as in time of Peace by his Lawes, without any manner of diminution: And this belongs to him to do ſo, as an eſſential part of his Office, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Laws of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Edward,</hi> in theſe words,<note place="margin">Leg. <hi>Edw.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> de offic. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</note> 
               <hi>Rex quia Vicarius ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Regis eſſe, debet de jure omnes terras, &amp; honores omnes, dignitates Jura, &amp; Libertates Coronae Regni hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus in integrum cum omni integritate, &amp; ſine diminutione obſervare, &amp; defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That if the Rights of the Crowne be hurt, decayed or loſt, the King is bound as well in duty as by his Oath, to the uttermoſt of his Power to endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of them to their ancient eſtate; And this is to be done, as well for the ſafety and benefit of his people, as for his own honour and dignity, as may appear by the Petition of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Parliament of 14<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. in whoſe Raigne the Crown ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much loſſe and dammage;<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>14.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> n. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> where they deſire, <hi>That the Prerogative of the King and of his Crowne may be
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170328:68"/> kept, And that all things done or attempted to the contrary might be redreſsed, and that the King be as free as any of his Progenitors were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the King is to keep and maintaine the Rights and Liberties of the Church and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> conſiſting not only in their Functions and Juriſdictions, but in their Lands and Revenues.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Laws and Cuſtomes of the Realme, <hi>which the people have made and choſen,</hi> are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood only of thoſe Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes then in being at the time of the taking of that Oath: For theſe Reaſons;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The words are in the Preterper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Tenſe, <hi>which the people have made and choſen,</hi> not in the Future Tenſe, which they were hereafter to make, and which the King could not ſwear to keep, till he knew what they were.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The words are chiefly meant of ſuch Laws and Cuſtomes which lay in uſage and immemoriall preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170328:68"/> which have their eſſence and life from time paſt; For no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes can begin by Law in time to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They were ſuch Laws and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes which the King at the time of the taking of this Oath had a Legall power to judge of and determine, whether thoſe Laws were good or bad; for the evill Laws and Cuſtomes <hi>he was wholy to put out,</hi> which muſt of neceſſity be referred to the time paſt or preſent: for of future things he could poſſibly have no knowledge; Where alſo by like neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it follows, that the King hath a Supreame Vote in all Laws whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to judge whether they be good or evill, for his Crown, his Church and Kingdome, and accordingly to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or diſaſſent, or elſe it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to avoid the Crime of Perjury.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The King ſhall grant no Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but where he may do it by his Oath; Now the Charter there meant, is the Charter of Pardon, granted by the King in the Caſes of Manſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170328:69"/> Robberies,<note place="margin">6. E. 1. Stat. <hi>de Gloc.</hi> c. 9.2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat. de Northton.</hi> c. 2. 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 13.10. <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 2.14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 15.</note> Fellonies, and other treſpaſſes againſt the Peace; And what in theſe Caſes ſhall be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Kings Oath, and what not, is reſolved and determined by divers Acts of Parliament, which I have Quoted in the Margin.</p>
            <p>So that by all I have ſaid it plainly appears, that the King in reſpect of his Duty and Office, in reſpect of his Oath, in reſpect of the Dignity and Honour of his Crown, and the good of his People, is to Governe them by the Laws of the Land. And ſo have I made good my ſixt and laſt Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170328:69"/>
            <head>THE CONCLUSION TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo I hope I ſhall find you in pardoning any errour or miſtake which may happen in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe againſt my will; when I ſhall acquaint you that it was Penned in the time of my Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and my Chamber, Study, and Books in the middle Temple Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred from me.</p>
            <p>In that very time when the greateſt Monarch of all <hi>Europe,</hi> even the King of Great<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Azor. Tom.</hi> 2. l. 11. c. 5. Col. 1668.</note> Britane was become a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, Great by Extraction of Birth, being legally and ſucceſſively deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170328:70"/> from above an hundred Kings; Great in the abilities of his mind, but Greateſt of all in Piety, Patience, Wiſdome, Fortitude, and other love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Graces and Virtues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the loſs of whoſe Liberties I evidently ſaw the loſs of the Peoples: for the which, I had not long before ſuffered by defending their Liberties againſt the Uſurpations of the High-Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>I hereupon thought it incumbent upon my ſoul to defend the Rights of the <hi>Crown of England;</hi> the huge ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter of the <hi>Peoples Liberties,</hi> unto which, I held my ſelf bound in <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> by a double Caution; Firſt to my Prince by my Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegeance,</hi> which I had taken five times; part of which are <hi>to aſsist and defend all Juriſdictions, Praeheminencies and Authourities an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Imperiall Crowne of this Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to my Borough of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke,</hi> where I was freely choſen their Burgeſſe for that Parliament, and maintaining theirs and the whole Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170328:70"/> Liberties annexed to that Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne; part of which Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to maintaine their Rights. Of which, that bleſſed Prince gave a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall teſtimony, by profeſſing at the time of his death, <hi>That he died a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr for the Liberties of his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After whoſe death; I ſaw with grief, what I ever feared would come to paſs with Horrour; Liberty, Truth, and Peace, ſo much cried up and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, quickly turned into Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs, Lies and War: their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties confirmed to them by above thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Parliaments, and holden for divers hundreds of years by the Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they at that time held them by no other Tenure, than the <hi>ſharper Sword,</hi> and the ſtronger Arme.</p>
            <p>Me thinks good Reader I ſtill heare in my eares the wofull cry of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England</hi> at that time, much like that in the Lamentations of <hi>Jeremy, The Crowne is fallen from our Head, the breath of our Nostrils is gone: woe unto us that we have ſinned.</hi> And this we long continued amongſt us, and had done ſo ſtill, had not God
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170328:71"/> who giveth ſalvation to Kings, and by a miracle of Mercy ſent us a Deliverer our now gratious Soveraigne, whom like another <hi>David,</hi> he had often ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the hand of <hi>Saul,</hi> and from his hurtfull Sword. And therefore you, and I, and all the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as we have wonderfull cauſe to praiſe God for him; ſo have we cauſe mightily to pray for him. That Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God who hath appeared to him like to another <hi>Moſes,</hi> as well in the <hi>Flags</hi> as in the <hi>Buſh,</hi> and delivered his ſoul from death, &amp; his feet from falling, would bleſs him with ſuch a ſpirit of Government, that Judgment may run down as <hi>Waters,</hi> and Righteouſneſs as a mighty ſtreame in all the parts of his Dominions. And likewiſe would bleſs all his People with ſuch a ſpirit of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,<note place="margin">Iſai. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>That they may beate their Swords into Plowſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-hooks; and that they may not learne War any more.</hi> But that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the <hi>deformity</hi> of War, the Beauties of Grace and Glory may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dwell in our Land.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:71"/>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:72"/>
            <p>The Rights of the Crowne.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:72"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> Theſe Books following, are Printed for <hi>Simon Miller,</hi> and Sold by him at the Starre in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Small Folio.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Lightfoot</hi> his Harmony on the New Teſtament, which will ſhorely be re-printed with large Additions.</p>
               <p>Aſtrology reſtored; or an Introduction to the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Stars in four Books, by <hi>William Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p>The civil Wars of <hi>Spain</hi> in the Reigne of <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth, Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of that Nation, wherin our late unhappy differences are paralleled in many particulars.</p>
               <p>A general Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the year 767 to the death of K <hi>James, &amp;c.</hi> By <hi>David Hume</hi> of <hi>Godſcroft.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Age, wherein is ſet down the true ſtate of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> as it was in the year 1500 alſo the cauſes of all the Warres and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions that have happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this preſent time; with the memorable ſieges and battels; together with the lively Effigies of the moſt renowned perſons.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul Baine</hi> his practicall Commentary on the whole Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt pleaſant and profitable Hiſtory of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,</hi> wherein all the vices that uſually attend youth are plainly laid open, that the misfortunes of ſome may teach others to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon vice, done into Engliſh by a perſon of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>Eighteen Books of the Secrets of Art and Nature, being the ſumme and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Naturall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, firſt deſigned by Doctor <hi>John Wecker,</hi> and now much enlarged by Doctor <hi>R. Read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queen of <hi>Arragon,</hi> a Play in <hi>folio.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:170328:73"/>
               <head>In Quarto large.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jo. Barklay</hi> his <hi>Argenis,</hi> Tranſlated by Sir <hi>Robert le Griſe</hi> Knight, by his Late Majeſties ſpecial Command with Figures or without.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quarto Small.</head>
               <p>An Experimental Treatiſe or Surgery, by <hi>Felix Wortz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith, or the good Old Religion <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Nicholſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The Anatomy of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: By <hi>George Siroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eatiſes: 1 The Converſion of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> touching Prayer and Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 2. Gods Trumpet ſounding to Repentance. 3. Sovereign preſervatives againſt diſtruſtful thoughts and cares: By <hi>Will. Atterſoll</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Isfield</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aynſworth</hi> on the <hi>Cantic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul Baine</hi> his <hi>Dioceſans</hi> Trial</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gr lle</hi> againſt <hi>Appolonius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Treatiſe of Civil po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Samuel Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Politick and Military Obſervations of Civil and Military Government, containing the Birth, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, Decay of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, the carriage of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Pinchin</hi> his Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious price of mans Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, cleared.</p>
               <p>Aſtrology Theologized, ſhewing what nature and influence the Starres and Planets have over men, and how the ſame may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and avoided.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wells</hi> his Souls Progreſs.</p>
               <p>Chriſt tempted, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Conquered; Being a plain Expoſition on the fourth Chapter of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Goſpel: By <hi>John Gumbleden</hi> Min. of the Goſ.</p>
               <p>The Saints Society.</p>
               <p>D. <hi>Stoughtons</hi> thirteen choice Sermons, with his Body of Divini y.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, together with the anſwer of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of mans Redemption by <hi>Edward Holioke</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Camdens</hi> Remains.</p>
               <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th doctrin of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſweetly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monizing with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith of all the
<pb facs="tcp:170328:73"/> Proteſtant Reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>The Philoſophicall Touchſtone; or Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon Sir <hi>Kenelme Digbye</hi>'s Diſcourſes of the nature of bodies, and of the reaſonable ſoul, by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Roſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Saints Triangles of dangers, deliverances, and duties, by <hi>Nathaniel Whiting</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The Confeſſion of Faith, of all the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> agreed upon at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> 1659.</p>
               <p>The Deſcription of the Univerſal Quadrant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Tho. Stirrup</hi> Mathem.</p>
               <p>The whole Art of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, painting, limning and etching: collected out of the choiſeſt Italian and Germano Authours, by <hi>Alex Brown</hi> Practitioner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Large Octavo.</head>
               <p>A Treatiſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Promiſes: By <hi>Edw. Leigh</hi> Eſq;.</p>
               <p>The Rights of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as it is eſtabliſhed by Law, by <hi>Edward Bagſhaw</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner-Temple, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice to the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Florus Anglicus,</hi> with the Lively Effigies of all the Kings and Queens, ſince the conqueſt, cut in braſſe.</p>
               <p>The Reconciler of the Bible, wherein above two thouſand ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions are fully and plainly Reconciled.</p>
               <p>Evidences for Heaven, containing infallible ſigns, and real demonſtrations for Aſſurance of Salvation, publiſhed by <hi>Edm. Calamy</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Life and Reign of King <hi>Charls,</hi> from his Birth to his Death, by <hi>Lambert Wood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Night-ſearch, the ſecond part: by <hi>H. Mill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A view of the Jewiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, with their Rites, Cuſtoms and Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>Uſefull Inſtructions for theſe Evil times, held forth in 22. Sermons, by <hi>Nich. Lockyer,</hi> Provoſt of <hi>Eaton</hi> Colledge</p>
               <p>The Nullity of Church-Cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, or Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, not of Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but a meer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention: Written by the famous <hi>Tho. Eraſtus,</hi> and never before Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:170328:74"/>
               <head>Small Octavo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ed Waterhouſe</hi> Eſq; His Diſcourſe of Piety and Charity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panacea,</hi> or the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Medicine; being a Diſcourſe of the Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature and Virtues of Tobacco: By Dr. <hi>Everard</hi> and Others.</p>
               <p>A view and Defence of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> very uſefull in theſe times.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Pet. du Moulin,</hi> his Antidote againſt Popery; publiſhed on purpoſe to prevent the Deluſions of the Prieſts and Jeſuites who are now very buſie among us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vinditiae Gratiae Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalis duobus Tractatulis comprehenſae.</hi> 1. <hi>De effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciâ Sacramentorum in genere.</hi> 2. <hi>De efficaciâ Baptiſmi, quantum ad parvulos quibus praefigitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiſtola Reverendiſſimi Patris</hi> Johannis Davenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti <hi>nuper Epiſcopi</hi> Sarisburi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herberts</hi> Devotions, or a Companion for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, containing Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and prayers uſefull upon all occaſions.</p>
               <p>Rare verities; or the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of Venus unlockt, and her ſecrets laid open.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Extraneus Vapulans,</hi> or the Obſervator reſcued from the violent but vain aſſault of <hi>Haman Leſtrange</hi> Eſq;, and the back-blows of D. <hi>Bernard</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Dean: by <hi>P. Heylin</hi> D.D.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid de Ponto,</hi> in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The Loves of <hi>Clerrio</hi> and <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zio</hi> a Romance.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Knowles,</hi> his Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Hebrew Tongue.</p>
               <p>A Book of Scheams or Figures of Heaven, ready ſet for every four Minutes of times, and very uſefull for all Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Florus Anglicus,</hi> or an exact Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> from the Reign of <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour to the death of the Late King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lingua,</hi> or the Combate of the Tongue, and five Senſes for Superiority: a ſerious Comedy.</p>
               <p>The Spirits Touchſtone; being a clear diſcovery how a man may certainly know whether he be truly taught by the Spirit of God, or not.</p>
               <p>The poor mans Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb facs="tcp:170328:74"/> and Chyrurgion.</p>
               <p>Phyſical Rarities, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the moſt choice Receipts in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, for the cure of all Diſeaſes Incident to mans body: By <hi>R Williams.</hi> To which is added the phyſical Mathematicks: By <hi>Hermes Triſ-Megiſton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Idol of Crowns, or the Relation of <hi>Wat Tiler</hi>'s Rebellion.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, in 3 parts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onian</hi> Catechiſm in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The life of that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable man, <hi>Fauſtus Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enenſis,</hi> deſcribed by a <hi>Polonian</hi> Knight.</p>
               <p>The Golden Fleece, or a Diſcourſe of the cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi> his Divine Meditations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vigerius Precepts</hi> of <hi>Idio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grotij Poemata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three Books of M. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Swanſey</hi> in <hi>South-wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 The Meſſiah Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the mouthes of Babes in <hi>America;</hi> or <hi>Gaius</hi> and <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> a helpfull Father, and his hopeful Son, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of the three moſt conſiderable points. 1. The great want of Chriſt. 2 The great worth that is in Chriſt. 3. The good way that is chalkt out by Chriſt</p>
               <p n="2">2. The New Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall Church, prov'd to be the old Chriſtian Church, by Scripture, Reaſon, and Hiſtory.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Rending Church-member Regularly call'd back to Chriſt and his Church.</p>
               <p>A phyſical Dictionary.</p>
               <p>An exact Hiſtory of the ſeveral changes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>England,</hi> from the horrid Murther of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, to the happy Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, with the Renowned Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of General <hi>Monck,</hi> by <hi>F. D.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Duodecim.</head>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Smith</hi>'s practice of phyſick.</p>
               <p>The Grammar War.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſſelius Apothegmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faſciculus Florum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Craſhaw</hi>'s Viſions.</p>
               <p>The Juniper Lecture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helvicus Colloquies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The torments of hell ſhaken; or a Diſcourſe with many proofs, ſhewing that there is not a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after this life for any
<pb facs="tcp:170328:75"/> to endure that ſhall never end, by <hi>Samuel Richardſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The underſtanding Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians duty, often to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate the death and paſſion of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus; with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary preparatives there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Souldier, his Combate with the three arch-enemies of man-kind, the world, the fleſh, and the devil.</p>
               <p>Seaſonable advice to the Apprentices of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City of <hi>London,</hi> touching their duty to God, and their Maſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heinſius de Crepundi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> or the Government of the Emperour of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> with the manner and faſhions of the people of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drexeliu</hi>'s ſchool of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drexelius</hi> his right In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of every ones acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>A School or Nurture for Children, or the Duty of Children, or the Duty very uſefull for all that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to bring up their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fear of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Viginti Quarto.</head>
               <p>The New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>The third part of the Bible.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Richard Bakers</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and Prayers for every day of the Week.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Playes.</head>
               <p>The Ball.</p>
               <p>Chawbut.</p>
               <p>Conſpiracy.</p>
               <p>Obſtinate Lady.</p>
               <p>The <hi>London</hi> Chanticlers: a Comedy foll of various and delightfull Mirth, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before publiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:170328:75"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
